<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Comfort from the cradle, as well as from the crosse of Christ. Being meditations upon Isaiah 9.6. / The substance whereof was delivered in two sermons. Preacht at VVinchester upon the feast of the Nativitie last past. By Tho. Bradley Dr in Divinitie, lately one of His Majesties chaplaines, and Rector of Castleford and Ackworth neere Pontefract in Yorke-shire.</title>
            <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E637_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 98:E637[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Comfort from the cradle, as well as from the crosse of Christ. Being meditations upon Isaiah 9.6. / The substance whereof was delivered in two sermons. Preacht at VVinchester upon the feast of the Nativitie last past. By Tho. Bradley Dr in Divinitie, lately one of His Majesties chaplaines, and Rector of Castleford and Ackworth neere Pontefract in Yorke-shire.</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1650 [i.e. 1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "1651"; the "0" in the date has been written over with a "1".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah IX, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112840:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COMFORT FROM THE CRADLE, AS WELL AS FROM THE CROSSE of CHRIST. <hi>Being</hi> Meditations upon <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſubſtance whereof was delivered in</hi> TWO SERMONS. <hi>Preacht at</hi> WINCHESTER <hi>upon the Feaſt of the</hi> NATIVITIE <hi>laſt paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THO. BRADLEY D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> in Divinitie, lately one of His Majeſties Chaplaines, and Rector of <hi>Caſtleford</hi> and <hi>Ackworth</hi> neere <hi>Pontefract</hi> in <hi>Yorke-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by H.H. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112840:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112840:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, The Lady FRANCES Daughter to the Right Honourable IOHN LORD SAVILE Baron of PONTEFRACT, &amp;c. his Deare Wife, <hi>The Preacher wiſheth a portion in all the Grace, and comfort in the enſuing Diſcourſe diſcovered.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>DEARE LADY,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not my buſineſſe in this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, either to excuſe my am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition in looking ſo high, or to juſtifie your diſcretion in ſtoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo low, till two ſuch unequals met together in a Conjugall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, there was a time when ſuch a meeting need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no apologie, when it was no wonder for our Tribe to match into Noble ſamilies nor diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:112840:3"/> for Noble Families to match into our Tribe, among all the Tribes of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> none but that (the Tribe of <hi>Levy</hi>) was allowed to match into the royall Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> by which previledge <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the Prieſt had to wife<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chr. 22.11</note> 
               <hi>Iehoſhabeah</hi> daughter to <hi>Iehoram,</hi> &amp; ſiſter to <hi>Ahaziah</hi> Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> The very<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Amoz,</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Amazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> King of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah.</hi>
               </note> Prophet and Penman of my text (if the Jewiſh records deceive us not) was of the blood Royall, and the greateſt<note n="b" place="margin">Presbyter Iohn.</note> Prince this day in the world, counts it his highest honour (and it is the first in the Catalogue of all his high titles) to be ſtiled<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtants Anr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtes Sacerdos. Atiqua nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſummum huic officio tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buunt honore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prieſt.</hi> True it is we are falne into other times, which<note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 13.33, 34.</note> 
               <hi>by making the loweſt of the people Prieſts, have made the Prieſts the loweſt of the People:</hi> but you know whoſe ſinne that was, charged and rechar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſo home upon him,<note place="margin">Ieroboam.</note> as the very cauſe of his ruine, and remaines in the ſtory of his life, as a blot in his Armes, and a ſtaine to his honour to this very day. I confeſſe (notwithſtanding) it had beene honour enough for mee to have beene your Chaplaine. The nobleneſſe of your birth, with other perfections ſuitable might well have commended you to any, my Lords your
<pb facs="tcp:112840:3"/> Father or Brothers Peeres in this Kingdome, but ſeeing providence had otherwiſe determined, as the<note n="d" place="margin">As God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed ſo we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed.</note> Poſie of your wedding Ring, of your owne choyce (if at leaſt it be not<note n="e" place="margin">She ſuffered deeply in both, but both never troubled mee till I loſt my Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (of choyce bookes, and of good value, by the treachery of a pretended friend, but a cloſe <hi>hypocrite</hi> and notorious <hi>temporizer,</hi> one <hi>Lake</hi> of <hi>Caſtleford</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, who upon higheſt engagements undertooke to preſerve them for mee, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the turning of the times, and the taking of <hi>Pontefract Caſtle,</hi> betrayed his truſt, and kept them from mee, and that not for the uſe of the publike but for his owne, after he had concealed them for mine, above two yeares and had them in his hands ſo concealed, when my other goods were ſequeſtred, and he a prizer of them.</note> ſequeſtred nor plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered among the reſt) will daily put you in mind. I am glad to ſee you do ſo contentedly ſit down with your lott, and beare with patience the croſse that is laid upon you, while I (as duty binds mee) and as in good reaſon I ought) help to beare one end of it with you. And now, Lady, ſince by this means I have undone you (and the times will needs have it ſo) I know no way better how to make you amends, then by becomming an instrument to help forward your faith, a meanes to further you in the waye of life. And if in the loſſe of all our <hi>earthly</hi> comforts and contentments, we can compaſse thoſe that are <hi>heavenly,</hi> if in the want of all the joyes of this world, and the ſeeming happineſſe in the things here below, we can make it an occaſion to ſeek the more earnestly after heavenly happineſſe, and the joyes which are from above, wee ſhall be still happy in our ſufferings, and gainers by
<pb facs="tcp:112840:4"/> being<note n="*" place="margin">Periiſſem niſi periiſſem. <hi>Themiſt. Athen.</hi>
               </note> looſers. It was your owne expreſsion, and I muſt not forget it; that the hope which you did conceive of advantaging your ſelfe in your ſoules health, and of being furthered in the way to heaven, was the maine inducement which prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with you, to looke upon a man of my profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in that way that you did. And it is (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) my duty, and I muſt not neglect it, carefully to endeavour ſo to ſatisfie that your expectation, as that you may not be altogether diſappointed of that hope, in performance of which duty, and part of payment of which debt, I ſend you here theſe two mites, not doubting your acceptance, both for his ſake from whom they come, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the Image ſake, and ſuperſcription which they beare, and that is not of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Caeſar,</hi> of <hi>A Child</hi> on the one ſide, and <hi>A Sonne</hi> on the other, the maine ſubject of the enſuing text, and diſcourſe upon it. A viſit to your two ſonnes at <hi>Wincheſter</hi> gave the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of coyning them,<note n="*" place="margin">The eldeſt borne at <hi>Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> on <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> day <hi>1632.</hi>
               </note> one of which was borne on that very day, ſet apart by the Church for cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating the memoriall of the birth of <hi>this</hi> child, and if it were not reproveable in <hi>Herod</hi> to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate
<pb facs="tcp:112840:4"/> his birth-day (as the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> ſilence in that particular, recording the ſtory of it) ſeemes to me to conclude) and if the <hi>marvailous works of the Lord be ſuch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>that they ought to be had in remembrance,</hi> and to be kept in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and to be delivered over from Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Generation to be preſerved in remembrance, and the way which the wiſedome of God himſelfe hath appointed as moſt fit to doe this by, bath ever beene by anniverſary Commemorations yearly feasts, holy meetings,<note place="margin">Eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r 9.27.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> and Convocations for that purpoſe. I hope it will neither be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon the Church as a crime that it hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſuch a day for the celebrating of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of the birth of this child in my text, nor in mee, that I did my part then in ſpeaking, or now in writing in the honour of his <hi>Natitivity</hi> ſuch a ſubject I confeſſe might well become a better pen, and ſuch it hath, and ſuch many, but amongst many, and many better, there is ſtill mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enough for more, and roome enough for mine, which is ſo much the bolder, becauſe it writes (if not onely to you, yet principally) to you <hi>Deare Lady,</hi> ſome ſlips, and failings doubtleſſe may be
<pb facs="tcp:112840:5"/> found in it, in which notwithstanding, I deſire candidly to be interpreted, it may be there will be found ſome thing among hand, which may make amends for it, ſome thing which you doe not read every day, ſome thing which it is very neceſſary for your Sexe to know (eſpecially in the ſecond Sermon) ſomething which (I doubt not) will afford you much comfort, and good ſatisfaction, and that in ſome neceſſary but clouded truths, ſuch as it is what ever it be, yours it is moſt peculiarly, and to your hand and view I preſent it. Read it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Deare Lady,</hi> and in it my love to your Soule, my due reſpects to you, my tender care of you, and all that may ſpeake me most faithfully, really, and affectionately yours, deſiring of Almighty God, that you may receive as much comfort, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and aſſurance, out of it as he that pen'd it hath grounded on it, and daily receiveth from it, who is and ever will be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all things according to the Covenant which once I made you THOMAS BRADLEY.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>OXFORD</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> the firſt <hi>1650.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112840:5"/>
            <head>COMFORT FROM THE <hi>CRADLE,</hi> AS WELL AS from the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of CHRIST: Being MEDITATIONS upon</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ESAIAH 9.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>For unto us a Child is borne,</l>
                  <l>Vnto us a Sonne is given.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the Prophets that aroſe in the Church from <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie,</hi> there was none that had more cleare viſions of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> than this the Penman of our Text, the Prophet <hi>Iſayah,</hi> who ſpake and writ of him more like an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt than a Prophet, as if he were to deliver (not a Propheſie of things to come, but rather<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Is borne, is given,</hi> ſayes this Text, whereas he was not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally borne till <hi>700</hi> yeares after.</note> a hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of things already done, and long ſince accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112840:6"/> hence it is that he is uſually called <hi>The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall Prophet.</hi> And it is no idle conjecture, that in reference to this he had his name, (not by chance) but by ſpeciall providence aſſigned him, <hi>Iſayah,</hi> which (if you will read in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jeſchaiah,</hi> &amp; imports as much as <hi>ſalus Domini, The ſalvation of the Lord,</hi> or as ſome read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiahu, Conſervet Dominus,</hi> or, <hi>det Dominus ſalutem, Let the Lord ſave, les the Lord give ſalvation;</hi> namely, according to his good word unto this Prophet, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manifold viſions concerning the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> revealed unto him, and the cleare prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of him contained in this booke. It is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that out of this Prophet there are no leſſe then<note n="*" place="margin">Muſculus in Iſayam.</note> ſixtie teſtimonies alleaged by our Lord and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in the New Teſtament, which is more then they have done out of any other of the Prophets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides (one onely excepted) namely the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> out of whoſe booke of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> there are alleaged ſixtie foure, and out of both ſo frequently for the ſame reaſon, becauſe they writ more clearly, more fully, more diſtinctly, of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> then any of the reſt of their brethren the Prophets had done. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all, there is not found a more famous propheſie concerning him then this wee have under hand, in the words which I have read unto you, where you have him preſented to you in the very cradle. <hi>For</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Vnto us a Child is borne,</l>
                  <l>Vnto us a Sonne is given.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of theſe words you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112840:6"/> muſt conſider well the occaſion of them, and to what purpoſe the Prophet brings them in at this time, and that was to comfort the King in a caſe of diſtreſſe, as you may gather out of<note n="*" place="margin">The hiſtory there refers to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie here.</note> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. and this was the caſe: <hi>Ahaz</hi> King of <hi>Iudah</hi> was at this time brought very low, being ſore oppreſt by the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> with one of which hee had lately fought a great battaile, wherein hee had the worſe of it, ſo farre the worſe that hee loſt 120000 men upon the place,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 28:</note> beſides 200000 more of all ſorts taken priſoners, and carried away captives, ſo great a blow as that he was afraid it might not onely weaken his Kingdome in his hands, but even ſhake the foundation of the Monarchie for ever. In this caſe hee comes to the Prophet for councell and for comfort, and the Prophet gives him both, and the grounds of both hee fetcheth from the child in my text: he bids the King be of good comfort, and that the loſſe of that day ſhould not ſo much trouble him, nor the feare of the ill conſequence which hee did miſdoubt might fall thereupon, in as much as there was a child borne in whom he ſhould be relieved in all this; A mighty Prince that ſhould do valiently, that ſhould raiſe amongſt them a greater and more glorious Kingdome then that was when it was at the higheſt, that ſhould fight againſt the enemies of it a more terrible battaile then that which hee had fought, and win upon them a more glorious victory then he had loſt: (though not with ſword and ſpeare,<note place="margin">Iſay 1.25.</note> but with ſword and fire, with a two-edged ſword, proceeding out of his mouth,<note place="margin">Iſay 4.4.</note> and with the <hi>ſpirit of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112840:7"/> burning,</hi> the ſpirit of grace &amp; power conquering by the Goſpell: all this in the fift verſe, <hi>Every battaile of the warriour is with confuſed noyſe, and garments rolled in blood, but this ſhall be with burning, and fewell of fire:</hi> And then in the ſixt verſe hee tells you who it is that ſhall execute all this, &amp; that is the Child in the Text, whom he deſcribes by nine glorious attributes in all and every of them making him out a mighty Prince indeed. <hi>The government ſhall be upon his ſhoulders, and his name ſhall be called Wonderfull, Counſellour, the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, the Everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace. Of the increaſe of his government, and peace there ſhall be no end, Hee ſhall ſit upon the Throne of David, and upon his Kingdome to order it, and to eſtabliſh it with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and juſtice from henceforth even for ever.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet under the type of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> preacheth to the King the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi>
               </note> The Prophet all this while, and in all this (under the type of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> a hopefull Prince, and as yet but a child) with ſingular art preaching Chriſt unto him, and propheſying of the glory and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Kingdome, (the ſpirituall Kingdome of the Church) for the protection and preſervation of which he ſhould doe wonderfully. To him the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet leads the King now in the day of his diſtreſſe, as to a ground and pillar of hope, &amp; comforts him in the advancement of the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, even againſt the loſſe of his owne. Be of good cheare. <hi>For unto us a Child is borne, unto us a Sonne is given.</hi> This was the method and the meanes by which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets before the comming of Chriſt were wont to comfort the people of God in the time of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by leading them unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by pointing them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112840:7"/> to the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> in whom was laid up all their hope and comfort, this was a <hi>ſtanding comfort</hi> in the Church which never failed them, a <hi>reſerve</hi> of hope, unto which in the time of their moſt grievous trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles they had recourſe and found reliefe: And hence it is obſerved, that the cleareſt viſions of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> have ever beene made out to the people of God in the darkeſt times: <hi>Jacob</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>Num.</hi> 23. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> in the wilderneſſe, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the captivity, ſaw more, and more clearly of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> then they did at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other time beſides: The Lord in his mercy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving appointed him as a ground of their hope and comfort againſt evill times: in the remembrance of whom they might ſtay themſelves untill his coming: And ſuch a time was it with <hi>Ahaz</hi> now; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch a method and means doth the Prophet uſe to comfort him: Be of good cheare, <hi>for unto us a child is borne, unto us a ſonne is given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (beloved) let us learne from this method of the Prophet how to comfort our ſelves and others in the like caſes, even by embracing this child in the armes of our faith, by flying unto Chriſt with the wings of our hope, and by having recourſe to the<note n="*" place="margin">Fundamentall mercies are ſure mercies.</note> ſure mercies of the <hi>Covenant</hi> purchaſed by his blood in it is laid up all our hope &amp; happineſſe, thats our reſerve and ſure refuge unto which we muſt truſt in an evill day, and well may, for it will not faile us. If ſuch a day come (and ſuch daies will come) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Prophets councell, turne thee to Chriſt, and turne to the covenant of grace, of which hee is the mediator, and conſider the pretious and glorious
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112840:8"/> things therein ſealed up and made ſure to thee, read there thine eternall election to grace and glory fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer then the mouniaines,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Covinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of grace the charter of the Church.</hi> Epheſ. 1.4. 1 Pet. 1.18. Tit. 3.7. Gal. 4.5. Pſal. 32.1. Luk. 10.10. Col. 1.12.</note> thy redemption by the blood of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> thy free juſtification by faith, thy reconciliation and peace made with God, thy adoption to the honour to become the ſonne of God, the remiſſion of thy ſinnes, thy name written in heaven, and thy infallible title to an inheritance in glory, all made over to thee, and all made ſure to thee in the Covenant of grace: all <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as the Greeke proverbe hath it) without the reach and danger of the dart, unſhaken grounds of hope and joy in the midſt of all the troubles, loſſes, and croſſes which in this mortall life you are ſubject unto, thinke upon theſe and be comforted, when all is loſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet there is left in theſe, which we cannot loſe, when the world hath done its worſt, ſomething yet it hath left us, which it could neither give, nor take away, enough (in the Prophets judgement here) to comfort a <hi>King,</hi> even in the loſſe of a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and in all that comfort have we all a ſhare as well as he, <hi>For</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Vnto us this Child is borne,</l>
                  <l>Vnto us this Sonne is given.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In which words here are three things which cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the eye, and at firſt view offer themſelves to our examination, take them in ſo many words.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Quis Who?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Quid What?</hi> and</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Quibus To whom.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 In the firſt of theſe we are to enquire <hi>who</hi> it is of whom the Prophet ſpeaketh this? and that the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112840:8"/> Text gives you in in two words, <hi>A Child, A Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 In the ſecond we are to conſider <hi>what</hi> it is that he ſpeaketh of him, and that he gives us in in two words more, <hi>is borne, is given, The Child is borne,</hi> but the <hi>Son</hi> is <hi>given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 In the third we are to examine to whom hee is ſo borne, and for whom he is given? and that wee have in a double expreſſion too, <hi>Nobis, to us;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, for failing, <hi>Nobis, to us; For unto us a Child is borne, unto us a Sonne is given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in order, and firſt of the firſt, <hi>Quis who?</hi> As ſometimes that noble <hi>Eunuch</hi> askt the queſtion, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.34. <hi>I pray thee of whom ſpeaketh the Prophet this? of himſelfe or of ſome other?</hi> ſuch is the queſtion here offered in the Text, of whom doth the Prophet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie this? of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> or of ſome other?</p>
            <p>Surely of ſome other ſayes the <hi>Iewe,</hi> which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will by no meanes heare of Chriſt yet come in the fleſh, and becauſe the Prophet ſpeakes in the praeter tenſe, <hi>is borne, is given</hi>) tels us, we muſt needs underſtand this of ſome child that was now actually borne and viſible in the world, and in that enquirie they pitch upon <hi>Hezekiah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> a child now of about<note n="*" place="margin">As by compu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation of time may be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of <hi>2 King. 18.</hi> compared with <hi>2 Chron. 28.</hi>
               </note> 13 yeares of age; as if the Prophet (like ſome flattering Court-Chaplaine, to pleaſe the King) did in theſe words but ſooth and ſmooth him up, by telling him what a glorious Prince his ſonne <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſhould prove, &amp; what a mighty and laſting Monarchie he ſhould raiſe, and be eſtabliſhed in.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this cavill, we do not deny but that the Prophet did all along in this propheſie allude
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112840:9"/> to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (a hopefull Prince) as to the type of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Prince farre more glorious, herein (with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar art) gaining the Kings eare, the more readily to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the doctrine of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Prophets ſingular art to gaine the Kings eare while hee preacheth Chriſt unto him.</note> when he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to him under ſo lovely and lively a type as his owne ſonne, whereby hee did not onely honour the Prince in making him the type of Chriſt, but leading the King on with delight in hearing ſuch glorious atchievements perſonated in his ſonne, hee prevailed with him the more readily to receive him that was perſonated by him, and while he opens his affections to the taking in of the one, he takes the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of it to convey in with him the other alſo, the type with the Antitype both together: wherein he acted the part of a wiſe charmer. Fiſhers of men ſhould be cunning, and have baits of all ſorts to catch ſoules withall; and (reſerving ſtill the innocencie of the dove) need had they bee wiſe as ſerpents, which have ſerpents to deale withall, which will ſtop their eares to the voyce of the charmer, charme hee never ſo wiſely.</p>
            <p>But that it could not be <hi>Hezekiah</hi> which was here principally intended, the ſequele of this verſe makes it cleare, where the wonderfull things ſpoken of this child, and the magnificent titles attributed to him in the deſcription of him, are too high and glorious to be aſcribed to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> or to any mortall man elſe.</p>
            <p>If I were to preach in a Synagogue of <hi>Iewes,</hi> mee thinks I ſhould need no more but foure other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies (to this in the Text) to convince them, and to demonſtrate the Child in my Text to be the <hi>Meſſiah</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112840:9"/> that was to come and none other, that child which above 3000 yeares before, the <hi>Lord</hi> promiſed to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to comfort him after his fall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. That child which to the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and Fathers of former generations was preacht and pointed at, in types and figures, promiſes and propheſies, ſacraments &amp; ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices under the law. That child whoſe day <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw a farre off (but dimly) as it were, through a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective glaſſe, and at a diſtance: that child which was the joy of the world, the expectation of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the hope of all the ends of the earth; that's the child which here the Prophet ſpeakes off, and in the Text preſents to us as viſibly as if (with old <hi>Symion</hi>) he had him in his armes, <hi>Unto us A Child is borne.</hi> And to this give all the Prophets witneſſe. <hi>Micah</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told long before, the place where he ſhould be borne, at<note n="*" place="margin">The very name of it did propheſie, and promiſe ſome ſingular good to us out of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies the <hi>home of bread,</hi> and out of it did hee come that was the bread of life.</note> 
               <hi>Bethlem, Micah</hi> 5.2. little <hi>Bethlem</hi> in this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable above all the Cities of all the other tribes,<note place="margin">Act. 10.34.</note> yea above <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it ſelfe, in that it was the birth-place of our bleſſed Lord: which therefore S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten calls <hi>Chriſti villula,</hi> Chriſts little village: Old <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> 1000 yeares before that foretold the time when he ſhould be borne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. when <hi>the Scepter was departed from Judah, and the Lawgiver from betweene his feet,</hi> not before. This our Prophet 19. Generations before he was borne, foretels us out of what ſtocke, tribe, &amp; family he ſhould come. <hi>Iſay</hi> 11.1. That hee ſhould be a branch ſpringing out of the roote of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> of the ſtocke and linage of <hi>David:</hi> And in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this Propheſie, and 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, hee comes nearer yet, and deſcribes the very
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112840:10"/> woman of whom he ſhould be borne, tels us, what manner of woman ſhe ſhould be, and what manner of child he ſhould be that was to be borne of her: that his mother ſhould be a <hi>Maid, Behold a virgin ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and beare a ſonne;</hi> and the child ſhould be a <hi>twin,</hi> and yet but one neither, but that one conſiſting of two natures united together in one perſon, and theſe natures as different one from the other, as heaven is diſtant from earth, and therefore had he a name aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him from heaven ſuitable to them both, and comprehending both of them in the ſignification of it. His name ſhall be called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Immanu-el.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then you have the time when, the place where, the tribe and family out of which this child ſhould be borne, you have him deſcribed by two diſtinguiſhing properties beſides, the one in the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther that ſhould beare him, the other in the child that ſhould be borne, by which he may be knowne from all other children in the world. Then wee need goe no further in this enquirie, lay all theſe together and compare them with what you read in the firſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Goſpel by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 1.</note> and the ſecond by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Luke,</hi> and you have found the child that we looke for,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> what here you have in the propheſie, there you have in the hiſtory. This day are all theſe Scriptures fulfilled in your eares. There is no ſtronger prop to our faith to confirme us in the truth of thoſe things which wee beleeve, then when wee ſee that thoſe things which are come to paſſe were ſo long before foretold that they ſhould ſo come to paſſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the great things which time hath brought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112840:10"/> forth ſince the creation of the world, there is nothing wherein this hath beene ſo punctually made good, as in the things concerning this child, of whom there is ſcarce any paſſage in his conception, birth, baptiſme, life, death, buriall, reſurrection or aſcention ſo ſmall, but wee can ſhew it you, either in promiſe, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, or type, or figure, or ſacrament, or ſacrifice, long before, many of them ſome thouſands of years before foretold and foreſhewed; whence it is that you read ſo often in the Goſpells ſuch expreſſions as theſe, <hi>That it might be fulfilled which was ſpoken by the mouth of ſuch a Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth: 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>and that it might be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led which was written by</hi> ſuch a Prophet:<note place="margin">Matth: 2.15.</note> That you may ſee how in all things concerning the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Propheſie and the hiſtory agree and anſwer each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as in a glaſſe) face to face:<note place="margin">Nor to be trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at, then the impudence of the Athiſt that dare call them into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note> In ſo much as there is nothing more to be wondered at, or indeed to be lamented, then the judiciall blindneſſe of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> which to this day doe not ſee theſe things, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> come in the fleſh, but doe with great earneſtneſſe ſtill looke for him out at the window, when he is long ſince come in at the doore: The Lord open their eyes that they may ſee him, and that <hi>they may looke upon him whom they have pierced,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>and and mourne for him abundantly, even as a mother mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for her ſonne, and as one that is in bitterneſſe for her firſt borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that they may do ſo, here it is neceſſary that we remove the ſcruple in the Text (which they ſtumble at) ariſing from the time wherein the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet gives you in his birth, which here he expreſſeth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112840:11"/> in the praeter tenſe as a thing done already, <hi>is borne, is given:</hi> whereas they ſay even the child that wee ſpeake of was not borne till about 700 yeares after this propheſie uttered: And it is true that they ſay, for if we ſearch the Chronologies of time, and the Genealogies of this Child,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.</note> we ſhall find there were 19 generations between this of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> in which the prophet propheſied this, and that of <hi>Mary,</hi> wherein and of whom this child was borne, which tooke up much about this time that they ſpeake of. But it is an uſuall thing with the penmen of the Holy Ghoſt eſpecially writing the hiſtoricall and propheticall parts of Scripture thus to expreſſe themſelves, and to ſpeake of things to come as if preſent, or paſt already by a figure uſually found in Scriptures, called <hi>Antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patio:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anticipatio.</note> But there is more in this expreſſion here in this place then a bare figure, the prophet hath a further meaning in it, and would thereby teach us, and point out unto us theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt the certainty of fulfilling the promiſe of his comming, that it was as ſure as if they had had him then amongſt them: what you have in hope grounded upon a promiſe from the all-ſufficient God, is as ſure as if you had it in hand, in whom all the promiſes are <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi> If the Lord hath ſaid it ſhall be done, write it done already, it is as ſure as if it were done,<note place="margin">Hab. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>though the viſion tarry, wait, for in the end it will ſurely come, it will not tarry.</hi> If the Lord hath ſaid, hee ſhall be borne, the Prophet dares boldly write him borne already, <hi>unto us A Child</hi> is <hi>borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112840:11"/>2 Secondly, to note the eternall efficacie of his birth, life, death, and paſſion, with all the other parts of his obedience, in reſpect of which he was not only <hi>A Child borne,</hi> but <hi>A lambe ſlaine from the beginning of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 5.2.</note> And (as the prophet <hi>Micah</hi> tels us) his goings forth were from the begining and from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, one would thinke that in this verſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet did ſpeake contradictions. In the beginning of it, he tels us he ſhall come, <hi>Out of thee ſhall he come that ſhall be captaine of my people,</hi> and in the latter end of it he tels us he is come already, come long agoe, his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings out have beene from the beginning, and from everlaſting, this cleare diſtinction reconciles the matter. There is a twofold comming of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> an <hi>Actuall comming,</hi> and <hi>A Vertuall comming. Actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> he ſhall come. <hi>Vertually,</hi> he is come already; <hi>His goings out have beene from the beginning, and from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi> the vertue and efficacie of his redemption reaching as well to the firſt man that was created in the world as to the laſt that ſhall ſtand upon the earth at the laſt day, even <hi>Adam</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was ſaved by his death: for of the ſalvation even of him (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his grievous ſinne and fall) wee nothing doubt, yea <hi>Origen</hi> hath recorded it, that (when he had finiſhed his daies on earth, and returned to the duſt from whence he was taken, he was buried in mount Calvery in the very place where (about 4000 years afterwards) the Croſſe of Chriſt was ſet whereon he was crucified. A wonderfull providence (if true) <hi>Ut primus virtute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanguinis Chriſti ſentiret qui primus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati author fuerit, That he might firſt feele the efficacie of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112840:12"/> Chriſts blood which was the firſt cauſe of ſhedding it.</hi> Hee did not then<note n="*" place="margin">That is, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficaciouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the distinction fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going.</note> firſt <hi>open the Kingdome of heaven to all beleevers when hee had overcome the ſharpneſſe of death,</hi> but when (by covenant made with his father, and concluded upon for the reconciling of the world) <hi>Hee tooke upon him to deliver man.</hi> And had it not been ſo, the patriarchs and fathers of former generations before his coming in the fleſh had beene very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy (with all their faith and hope, piety and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, holineſſe and obedience (in which they were exemplary) to be thruſt into <hi>Limbus,</hi> there to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for ſo many hundreds of yeares (as by the doctrine of the Church of Rome they muſt) untill Chriſt came thither with his Croſſe to breake open the priſon doores, and to ſet them free. They were in Chriſt before us, they ſaw his day and rejoyced, and not onely <hi>Iſay</hi> in his time, but the Fathers of the firſt ages of the world (long before him) embraced this child in the armes of their faith and hope, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, (as in the Text) <hi>Unto us this Child is born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, by this expreſſion doth the Prophet preach to us, and declare the omniſcience, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Lord God, with whom there is no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of time, nor any part of it paſt, or to come, but to whom all time is preſent, with whom one day is as a thouſand yeares, and a thouſand yeares but as one day, which ſees all things paſt and to come <hi>uno intuita</hi> at one view preſent before him; <hi>which calleth things that are not as if they were,</hi> which ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Cyrus, thou art my Shepheard, I have knowne thee and called thee by name:</hi> an hundred yeares before
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112840:12"/> 
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> was borne: neither is it in the power of any power under or in heaven ſo to ſpeak, but only of him who writes himſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I AM <hi>the</hi> Α <hi>Alpha, and the</hi> Ω <hi>Omega, the beginning and the end,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>the firſt and the laſt; which lifteth up his hand to heaven and ſaith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel: 1.</note> 
               <hi>I live for ever.</hi> And therefore upon this triall the Lord challengeth all the heathen gods, pretenders to dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Iſay</hi> 41.21. <hi>Produce your cauſe, ſaith the Lord, ſhew your ſtrong reaſons (ſaith the King of Jacob) let them bring them forth, and ſhew us what ſhall happen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 41.</note> 
               <hi>let them ſhew the former things what they be, that wee may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and know the latter end of them: or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them declare the things for to come, ſhew the things that are to come hereafter, that wee may know that ye are gods.</hi> A more convincing argument of the deity then that of miracles, in them there may be juggling, and <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> in many ſtrange things may goe as farre as <hi>Moſes:</hi> but to foreſee things to come at ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, at which it is impoſſible to ſee them in their cauſes, any farther then as it is the will and councell of him that hath ordained them, to bring them to paſſe according to his owne purpoſe, is the act and worke onely of a deity. When therefore you read in theſe words what the Prophet ſpeakes, do but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member withall from whom he ſpeaks, and you will be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Adde hereunto that the Prophet (though ſpeaking hereof the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> yet) alludes to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> the young Prince and lively type of him, in whom he is ſaid to be actually borne, as in his type and repreſentitive.</p>
            <p>In all which reſpects the expreſſion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112840:13"/> here is not only defenſible, but divine, &amp; high, full of grace and truth, and preacheth to the world Chriſt incarnate with power. The Angell ſeconds him <hi>Luke</hi> 2.11. <hi>Unto you is borne this day in the City of David, A Saviour, even Chriſt the Lord.</hi> And ſee, with what joy does hee deliver the newes of it? and how beautfull are his feet upon the mountaines, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the glad tidings of it? the whole univerſe ſeemes to be ſenſible of it, men and Angels rejoyce at it, and heaven and earth joyne together to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate his Nativitie: the ſtarre appeares, the Angels ſing, the heralds poaſt, the ſhepheards run, the Kings come in to bring their preſents, and to tender their homage to him in his very cradle. And ſhall it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveable in us this day to joyn with them in contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting our <hi>halleluiahs</hi> of joy and praiſe for our ſhare in this holy birth? or in the Church that it hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a ſet and ſolemne day for that purpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note n="*" place="margin">For there are that undertake to give us in more then that, the very minute in which he firſt opened the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, as <hi>Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> a famous Aſtronomour, who gives it in at <hi>15.</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes after <hi>10.</hi> at night, <hi>Virgo</hi> being then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendant <hi>in prima domo,</hi> in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary on <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Quadri. partite.</hi>
               </note> perhaps we cannot give you in preciſely (at this diſtance of time) the very day, or houre of the day wherein he was borne into the world? why it is not our purpoſe to calculate his nativitie, that wee ſhould be ſo preciſe in this matter, But to the honour of God, and for our owne comfort to preſerve and perpetuate the memory of ſo great a mercy, to renew our thankfulneſſe for the unſpeakeable good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed unto the world by it, to meditate upon the benefit of his conception, and incarnation, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce before the Lord, and in the Lord, for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and good will which thereby hee hath ſhewed to the ſonnes of men, duties which (though on no
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112840:13"/> day unſeaſonable, yet then ſurely moſt ſuitable, when (a day being ſet apart for thoſe duties) we ſet our ſelves apart for that day, and ſuſpending our thoughts from all worldly cares, and taking our ſelves off from all other diſtractions, wee bend our minds (with moſt ſerious devotion, and intended af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, to the performance of the duty of the day, in the day of the duty. And this is the day that calls for that duty at our hands, <hi>Come let us rejoyce and be glad in it;</hi> harke how the Angels ſing their <hi>Gloria in excelſis; Mary</hi> exults in her <hi>Magnificat,</hi> and why ſhould not we (amongſt them) beare a part in this heavenly Choyre for our part in this holy birth? Let us alſo with joy and praiſe ſing <hi>Glory to God on high,</hi> for his Peace (ſent) on earth below, and for his good-will ſhewed to the ſonnes of men, let our ſoules magnifie the Lord, and our ſpirits rejoyce in God our Saviour for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lanu, Lanu,</hi> unto us, even unto us <hi>This Child is borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SO then you ſee by the help of the Starre we have found the child we ſpake off:<note place="margin">The ſecond branch of the firſt generall part. <hi>The Sonne.</hi>
               </note> But what ſay you to the Sonne? whether is it the ſame with the Child here in the Text, or ſome other? and if the ſame, why doth the Prophet ſo ſuddenly vary in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion? but even now a Child, and preſently in the next word a Sonne, ſurely there's ſomething in it, what may be the meaning of it? Nothing at all (ſaith the <hi>Rabbi</hi>) but only this, in the firſt word,<note place="margin">Rabbi Kimhi.</note> he told you there was a Child borne, and in the next he tels you what manner of child it was, it was a man-child, a ſonne and not a daughter.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112840:14"/>1 But by the Rabbies leave there's more in it then ſo. If indeed the former word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>jelad,</hi> here rendred a <hi>Child,</hi> were of the Common-gender, as in our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh it is, and did ſignifie a woman-child as well as a man-child indifferently, then there were ſome ground for this conjecture, but if you examine the originall text you will find it otherwiſe, you will find that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>jelad</hi> is of the maſculine gender &amp; can ſignifie no other but a man-child. And ſo, for the Prophet to bring us newes that a man-child was borne, and preſently tell us it was a ſonne, were an unneceſſary tautologie, therefore there is more in it then ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There are which tell us, that by theſe maſculine expreſſions of a <hi>Manchild, A Sonne</hi> is intimated to us the honour and prerogative that the man hath above the woman in this buſineſſe, and the intereſt he hath in Chriſt before her, in that hee was borne a man-child, not a woman-child, a Sonne and not a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>But to this we anſwer, if this circumſtance may be a ground of an argument, whereby to prove the priviledge of either ſexe, and whether of them be nearer a kinnne to Chriſt, certainly it will conclude for the woman rather then for the man, for although our Lord tooke upon him the nature of a man in that ſexe, yet he tooke that nature of a woman, not of a man, yea without the help of man, and ſo hee hath united that ſexe unto himſelfe in a kind of conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which the man cannot chillenge. But Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath reconciled this difference, by dividing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112840:14"/> Chriſt equally between them thus. <hi>Virum aſſumendo, &amp; de foemina naſcendo, utrumque ſexum honoravit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus:</hi> Our Lord Chriſt by taking upon him the nature of man, and yet taking that nature of a woman, hath hereby equally honoured both ſexes, and ſhewed that they have both an equall intereſt in him, in Jeſus Chriſt in this reſpect, there is neither male nor fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male.</p>
            <p n="3">3 But yet wee have not ſounded the bottome of this myſtery, there is more in it yet then all this, let it be well lookt into, and it will be found, that in theſe two words is contained and taught the greateſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery that is in all the Chriſtian Religion, and that is the two really diſtinguiſhed natures united in the one and undivided perſon of our Mediatour, the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and the Divinity of the Sonne of God. <hi>Vnto us A Child is borne,</hi> there's his humanity: and, <hi>Vnto us A Sonne is given,</hi> theres his Divinity. As he was a child, ſo he was the ſonne of <hi>Mary;</hi> as a ſonne, ſo he was, (by eternall generation) the naturall Sonne of God: as a child, ſo he had a Mother, but was without a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as a ſonne, ſo he had a Father, but was without a Mother:<note place="margin">Heb.</note> and ſo was the true Antitype of him (in whom hee was long before typified) <hi>Melchizedek, without father, without mother, without generation:</hi> in reſpect of his humanity without a father, in reſpect of his Divinity without a mother, and therefore <hi>his generation who ſhall declare?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay.</note> No wonder if a few words after my text the Prophet tels us <hi>his name ſhall be called Wonderfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (as here in my text,) ſo all along throughout
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112840:15"/> the whole courſe of his life, fom his birth to his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, from his baptiſme to his death and paſſion you ſhall obſerve how this <hi>child,</hi> and this <hi>ſonne;</hi> the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and the <hi>Humanity of Chriſt,</hi> (like <hi>Hypocrates</hi> his twins,) goe hand in hand together.</p>
            <p>His birth was meane, his parents poore, there was no roome for them in the Inne, they are faine to take up a ſtable for their quarter; they find more kindneſſe among the beaſts, then among them that owed them, there is he borne, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold the Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But do you not ſee at the ſame time a ſtrange and new created ſtarre appeare in heaven waiting upon his birth, and the place where the child lay? and doe you not heare the Angels ſinging,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Gloria in excelſis,</hi> in honour of his Nativitie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold the Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.</note>As his birth was meane, ſo his accommodations are meaner, being borne he hath not a place where to lay his head. <hi>This ſhall be a ſigne unto you</hi> (ſaith the Angell) <hi>you ſhall find the babe wrapt in ſwadling clothes and laid in a manger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold a Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But do you not ſee at the ſame time, Kings by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration come from the Eaſt to doe him homage, do you not read how they brought their preſents to him, Gold, Frankincenſe, and Myrrhe; Gold repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Kingly office, Francumcenſe the Prieſtly, and Myrrhe the Propheticall office which hee was borne to,<note place="margin">The Kings of <hi>Arabia</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> ſhall bring gifts. <hi>Pſ. 45.</hi>
               </note> and which he was to beare and exerciſe in the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold A Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:112840:15"/>
            <p>When he was to be baptized he ſubmits himſelfe unto an ordinance, and to receive it at the hands of a man infinitely meaner then himſelfe, one that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he was not worthy to unlooſe the latchet of his ſhooe, yet without diſputing he goes into the water,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.</note> and is baptiſed of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold A Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But looke up and you ſhall ſee the heavens opened unto him, and the Spirit of God in the likeneſſe of a dove deſcending upon him, and you ſhall heare a voyce from heaven giving teſtimony of him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>This is my beloved Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold A Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When his parents (as the manner was) went up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to the feaſt of the Paſſeover, they tooke him along with them, he was numbred among other children, and as an ordinary child hee went in the multitude with the reſt, when his parents miſſing him rebuked him for it, hee ſubmitted to their repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and (as the text tels us,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note>) <hi>He came downe and was obedient to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold A Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But do you not read, how at the ſame time being but twelve yeares old, he went into the Temple, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelfe among the Doctors, diſputed with them, both hearing them and poſing them, asking them queſtions, reſolving their doubts, and that with ſuch gravity, ſuch ſatisfactory reſolution, as raiſed aſtoniſhment and admiration in all that heard him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold A Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:112840:16"/>
            <p>Laſtly, to conclude this paralele, at the time of his paſſion you ſee him under the hands, and power of his enemies, ſcourged, crowned, crucified, hanging on the Croſſe, bowing downe his head ſorrowing, complaining, weeping, bleeding, dying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold the Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But do you not ſee at the ſame time, the heavens grow blacke, and darkned above, and the earth trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling beneath him: do you not ſee the graves open, the rockes cleave in ſunder, the vaile of the Temple rent, and the whole univerſe ſeeme to be troubled at the ſadneſſe of the ſpectacle?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold the Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you ſee (not only in my text, but all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, the hiſtory of the Goſpell, and throughout the whole courſe of our bleſſed Redeemers life) the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord appearing in the cloud, the divinity of the Sonne of God breaking out through the cloud and veyle of his fleſh, and both of them clearly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting themſelves in the perſon of our Mediatour. And therefore (as the Father hath obſerved) when you ſee him crying in the cradle,<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> or crucifyed on the croſſe, when you ſee him hungry and thirſty, weary, weeping, ſorrowing, grieving, bleeding, &amp; dying, <hi>Ecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> homo, Behold A man:</hi> But when you ſee him caſting out Devils, raiſing the dead, feeding of thouſands with a few loaves, and fewer fiſhes miraculouſly multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: when you ſee him, reading the riddles of mens inmoſt thoughts, forgiving ſinnes, commanding not onely winds and ſeas, but uncleane ſpirits and devills unto obedience, then <hi>Ecce Deus, Behold A God:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112840:16"/> them both in my text in this child, and in this ſonne, <hi>Infans vagiens in cunabulo, filius tonans in Coelo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> A child crying in the Cradle, and hee at the ſame time A ſonne thundering in heaven: an Infant thruſt out of doores to take up his harbour in a ſtable, and he at the ſame time A Sonne diſpoſing of Paradiſe, and of the glorious manſions in heaven, at the right hand of his Father.</p>
            <p>And there was a reaſon for all this,<note place="margin">Reaſons of this marvelous uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the one undivided per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour.</hi>
               </note> yea there was a neceſſity of it on our parts; or elſ he could never have reconciled us to God the Father, nor have become for us a fit and perfect Mediatour. Neither the child without the ſonne, nor the ſonne without the child, could have done it, hee muſt be both, A Child, and A Sonne too, both God and man that was to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile God and man, heaven and earth together. Had he beene only man, he could never have laid downe a price which might have beene of ſufficient value to ranſome the ſinnes of the whole world, and had hee beene onely God, he had not had what to lay downe to ranſome them withall, not a body to offer up in ſacrifice for us, nor blood to ſhed, without which there is no redemption, (for the God head is impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible.) Had he beene onely man, he could never have gone through the great worke of our redemption, he could never have ſtood under the great weight of his Fathers wrath, and the burden of the ſinnes of the whole world, which were to be laid upon him. And had he beene onely God, he could not have ſatisfied the juſtice of God for the ſinne of man, which requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that ſatisfaction ſhould be made in that nature
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112840:17"/> that had offended: and what ſatisfaction had it been for God to ſatisfie himſelfe upon himſelfe, for the ſinne and offence that was committed againſt him by another? There was a neceſſity (therefore) that he ſhould be both, that the Child and the Sonne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the Humanity, and the Divinity united in one might make up the perſon of a fit <hi>Mediatour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 There was a neceſſity that hee ſhould be man that ſo he might punctually ſatisfie the juſtice of God for the ſinne of man, anſwering for ſinne in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that had committed it. <hi>Therefore A Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there was a neceſſity hee ſhould be God too, that by the dignity of his perſon hee might adde va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue to his ſufferings and obedience, to make them meritorious and of a ſufficient price to ranſome the ſinne of thouſands <hi>Therefore A Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 It was neceſſary he ſhould be man, that ſo hee might have what to offer up to God in ſacrifice for us, even a body capable of death, and blood to be ſhed for remiſſion of ſinne for the taking off of the ſentence of death that was gone out againſt us:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore A Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it was neceſſary hee ſhould be God too, that ſo by the power of his deity hee might ſupport his humanity in that great conflict, and under that great burden of his Fathers wrath, and the ſinne of the whole world that lay upon him, and that in the end he might be able to reſcue himſelfe out of the hands and power of hell, death, and the grave; and by his owne power to raiſe up his body from death to life; and openly to triumph over it. <hi>Therefore A Sonne.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112840:17"/> Therefore both, that hee might be a fit Mediatour betweene both, neither as God, ſo tendering the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Deity offended, as to forget the miſery of the poore loſt ſonnes of <hi>Adam:</hi> Nor yet as man, ſo compaſſionating the miſery of the loſt ſonnes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> as to neglect the honour of the Deity offended, but as one that was partaker of both, deare to both, and both to him, hee might lay an indifferent hand upon both, and ſo become betweene both, an aequall, indifferent, and impartiall Mediatour.</p>
            <p>And here (beloved) you have the revelation of that great myſtery, <hi>the myſtery of godlineſſe,</hi> the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writes to <hi>Tymothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without controverſie great is the myſtery of godlineſſe:</hi> and whats that?<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the fleſh:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>God in Chriſt reconciling the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>The Word made fleſh, Joh.</hi> 1. A myſtery indeed, which the Angels themſelves deſire to looke into, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith the Originall) to pry into, to the very bottome, implying, that the farther they pry into it, the farther they may, and the more ſtill they diſcover of the myſterie, affording matter of admiration, even to thoſe Angelicall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: And although wee are not able to looke ſo farre into this great myſtery as thoſe Angelicall ſpirits are, nor to diſcover ſo much of it as they doe, yet let it be ſeriouſly lookt into, and the diſcerning ſpirit will eaſily perceive how in this high myſtery all the moſt glorious Attributes of Almighty God doe meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and worke together, and in moſt eminent manner diſplay themſelves, how his wiſedome, his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112840:18"/> power, his juſtice, and his grace are all ſet aworke in this great deſigne, and the reſult of them all is, juſt the burthen of the Angels ſong, <hi>Glory to God on high, peace on earth beneath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>and towards men good will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt his wiſedome in laying the plot, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving the way how mankind loſt ſhould be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſaved, and yet he not ſuffer in the honour of his truth and juſtice which had paſt againſt them the ſentence of death, <hi>In quo die commederis morte morie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>In the day that thou eateſt, thou ſhalt die the death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, his power in bringing this about, being contrived, (againſt ſo great oppoſitions, ſo many difficulties ſtanding in the way) and effecting it with ſuch happy ſucceſſe as he hath done, though it coſt him deare.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, his juſtice in puniſhing ſin ſo ſeverely, and that in his owne Sonne, being but an underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker for it, and that meerly out of his love and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to poore ſoules loſt and undone, that they might not periſh.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, his grace in being at ſuch coſt to ſave and to reſtore ſinfull men his enemies, that had ſo highly offended him, and undone themſelves. All theſe may he that runneth read in this myſtery. There s in the 85. Pſalme, and 10. verſe, a ſweet paſſage of the Prophet <hi>David, Mercy and truth are met together, righteouſneſſe and peace have kiſſed each other:</hi> Behold in this myſtery they are met together, and in this glorious deſigne they kiſſe each other. His mercy ſuch, that rather then mankind ſhall periſh, his owne and onely ſonne ſhall become a Child, take their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112840:18"/> nature upon him, and in that nature ſuffer all, that mankind ſhould have ſuffered, and doe all that hee ſhould have done, that ſo all this being imputed unto him, he might have the benefit of it, that he might be excuſed from ſuffering, and accepted in the ſight of God as holy, as innocent, and as juſt, as if he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offended. And yet his juſtice ſuch, that rather then ſinne ſhall goe unpuniſhed, hee would puniſh it in his owne ſonne, yea and that with great ſeverity too, he would not ſpare him, although in the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the conflict he begg'd of him that he would, he deſired that that cup might paſſe from him,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.39.</note> yet he would not heare him, nor excuſe him, but laid on load of wrath and juſtice upon him, gave him up to the bitterneſſe of death, and lockt him up in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the grave, till hee had paid the uttermoſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our debt.</p>
            <p>See here how in this myſtery <hi>mercy and truth are met together, righteouſneſſe and peace</hi> (in this Child and in this Sonne) <hi>kiſſe each other.</hi> Behold how the wiſedome and the power, the juſtice and the grace of Almighty God all worke together, and proclaime with loud voyce, <hi>Glory to God on high.</hi> And theſe make up the firſt part of the Angels ſong.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of their ſong proclaimes good will unto men, and declares the unſpeakable good which by this myſtery they receive, and there are five great bleſſings and benefits which they receive by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, the ennobling of their natures: what an honour is this to our fleſh to be taken into union with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112840:19"/> the divine nature in the perſon of the Sonne of God? What an exaltation is this of our nature, that the Prince of Glory ſhould vouchſafe to cloth him ſelfe with it, and in it to appeare and converſe among the ſonnes of men? but how much more that in it hee hath victoriouſly triumphed over ſinne, death, hell, and the grave, that in it he is aſcended into heaven, and there ſitteth on the right hand of the Father, &amp; in that part of our fleſh which hee tooke hath taken poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of heaven for us, and (in our names) of the heavenly manſions which hee hath purchaſed and provided for us? <hi>Quid eſt homo? Lord what is man that thou ſhouldeſt thus conſider him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8 4.</note> 
               <hi>or the ſonne of man that thou ſhouldeſt thus regard him? thou haſt made him little lower then the Angels.</hi> Nay in this reſpect higher then the Angels, for <hi>he tooke not upon him the nature of Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but hee tooke upon him the nature of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, the ſeed of Abraham:</hi> hence ariſes a nearer affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (conſanguinity rather) betweene Chriſt and us, then is between Chriſt and the Angels, he becoming <hi>fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone,</hi> by this are wee made ſonnes of God, brethren of Chriſt, and coheirs with him of an Inheritance in glory.<note place="margin">Gen. 2 23. Epheſ. 5.30</note> This is an high priviledge, and a great benefit which wee receive by this myſtery. The enobling of our natures. And</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond is like unto this: The enabling of our natures to gratious and ſpirituall performances of holy and heavenly duties; for by vertue of this union of our natures with his, and his with ours, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re flowes from him into us an influence of grace, by which he (through his ſpirit) lives in us, and workes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112840:19"/> in us, by which he informes, actuates, and animates us, as the ſoule doth the body, of which it is the forme; hence followes the enabling of our natures to holy and ſpirituall performances; by vertue of this influence of grace, &amp; of Chriſt by his ſpirit living in us, and working in us, we are enabled to live that life which is according to godlineſſe, to mortifie our corruptions, to deny our ſelves with all our corrupt luſts and paſſions, to crucifie the fleſh, to deſpiſe the world with all the corruptions that are in it through luſt, to doe and to ſuffer for his name, above the power of nature by a higher power and principle of grace received from above. This is a ſecond benefit derived unto us from this myſtery.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is an intereſt in the Lord Jeſus, and with him in all that is his, in all his righteouſneſſe, merits, holineſſe, obedience, in all that he hath done and ſuffered for us, it is all ours, wee have a right in it, for from this union of our natures, there followes a Communion, and a common intereſt betweene us, of all that we have or are (which is communicable) by vertue of this union our ſinnes are laid upon him, and hee hath ſatisfied for them, and (on the other ſide) his righteouſneſſe is imputed unto us, and wee are juſtified by it. The Lord Jeſus by infuſing his ſpirit into us makes us<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4. Joh. 5.</note> 
               <hi>partakers of the divine nature:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The admirable manner by ashich the unio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> between Chriſt and his Church is wrought.</note> and againe, himſelfe taking our fleſh upon him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes partaker of our nature, and ſo there growes a neare union betweene us, he is ours, and we are his, he in us, and wee in him; as the vine with the branches, the husband with the wife, the body with the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112840:20"/> are one, ſo Chriſt and thoſe that are of Chriſt are one,<note place="margin">Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 5.30.</note> nay (with holy reverence be it ſpoken) wee are himſelfe, the expreſſion is high, but it is his owne, at leaſt breath'd from his owne ſpirit, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 12.12. <hi>As the body is one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>and hath many members, and all the members of that one body being many, are one body, even ſo is</hi> CHRIST: marke this Scripture well, it containes in it a truth more pretious then the gold of <hi>Ophir:</hi> the <hi>union</hi> (ſhould I ſay) nay more, the <hi>Identity</hi> of Chriſt with his Church, they make but one body: For the word <hi>Chriſt</hi> here in the text (as is clear by the context) doth not repreſent unto us Chriſt as a perſon, but is <hi>nomen collectivum,</hi> a collective name, comprehending in it,<note place="margin">The <hi>Identitie</hi> of Chriſt with the Church.</note> together with himſelfe his whole Church, with every child and member of the ſame, all making up but one body, <hi>even ſo is Chriſt,</hi> where (as if they were himſelfe) and he not himſelfe without them, ſee how hee vouchſafeth them his owne name, <hi>Even ſo is Chriſt:</hi> ſo hee calls them, and ſo hee counts them Oh the happineſſe and ſecurity of the poore Saints in this reſpect, they are rich enough, happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, when he is theirs who is the fountaine of all happineſſe, <hi>In whom are hidden all the treaſures of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and godlineſſe, and from whoſe fulneſſe, as at the well-head, they all receive grace for grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 The fourth benefit derived unto us out of this myſtery, is in the ſympathy that hence ariſeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and thoſe that belong unto him, for from this union and myſticall marriage of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures together, there followes a ſympathy betweene him and us, whereby that which is done to the one,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112840:20"/> is done to the other alſo, whether it be good or evill, <hi>he that receiveth you receiveth me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.40.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; he that diſpiſeth you deſpiſeth me,</hi> ſaith the Lord to, and of, the leaſt of thoſe little ones which belong to him, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give a cup of cold water to a Diſciple, under the name of a Diſciple, but Chiſt thanks you for it, as if you had given it unto him. <hi>For in as much as you did it to the leaſt of theſe little ones, you did it unto mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25 40.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. Againe, you cannot offer the leaſt wrong or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to any of them, but hee will taxe you for it, as if you had offered it to him too. If <hi>Saul</hi> be travelling to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> with commiſſion to perſecute the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, the head lookes downe from heaven and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou mee? Act.</hi> 9. not mine, but mee, becauſe mee in mine, thou woundeſt mee through their ſides. Oh that this ſympathy were reciprocall in us too, that the ſame mind were in us towards Chriſt Jeſus, which is in him towards us, that we could be ſenſible of the wrong, and diſhonour that is done unto him daily, as if it were done immediately unto our ſelves, ſo it was with the holy Prophet. <hi>The rebukes of them that fell upon thee fell upon mee</hi> And,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69 9.</note> 
               <hi>do not I hate them that hate thee? even as if they were mine enemies?</hi> Yes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.21.</note> I beare him witneſſe hee did, and for thoſe that loved and feared the Lord, hee loved them as well, and that <hi>eonomine,</hi> and <hi>qua tales,</hi> for that very cauſe, and in that reſpect, becauſe they did love,<note place="margin">Pſal 16.3.</note> and feare the Lord. Oh that we had that witneſſe within our ſelve that we did regard the cauſe of God, and the honour of God as this Prophet did, and that wee did ſhew
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112840:21"/> our love to God, by taking to heart the wrongs and diſhonours that are daily done unto him (in his Church, his Children, his Cauſe, his Ordinances, his Names, his Sabbaths, in all thar is deare unto him) as if it were done unto our ſelves, the Lord would ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take it very well at our hands, and reward that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affection ſeven-fold into our boſomes.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Laſtly, heres a ground of reverent boldneſſe, &amp; child-like confidence in our approaches to the throne of Grace, we can not draw neare to God, nor looke upon him in his Majeſtie, but wee ſhall be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by his glory <hi>(No man can ſee mee and live)</hi> but to God incarnate,<note place="margin">Exod. 33 20.</note> to God manifeſted in the fleſh, wee may, and live: wee cannot looke upon the body of the Sunne in his brightneſſe, but it will hurt our eyes to behold it, but wee may looke upon it in the water without danger: behold Chriſt in the fleſh is the <hi>Charactet of the Glory of the Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> and the expreſſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his perſon: through him wee may behold him, through him we have acceſſe unto him; and if we dare not be too bold with the Sonne, yet let us looke upon the Child, inviting us to the throne of grace, to partake of the plenty of his Fathers Court.</p>
            <p>Behold what a treaſury of Grace and Glory is here contained in this myſtery, what pretious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges we receive by it! what wonderfull fruits, and effects are brought forth by this wonderfull deſigne, all ſuitable to the greatneſſe of the meanes, by which they were wrought, and the high honour and dignity of the perſons which acted in it: no leſſe then the wiſedome of the whole Trinity, was ſet aworke in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112840:21"/> laying the plot, and contriving this great buſineſſe, no worſe then the Sonne of God himſelfe in his owne perſon, imployed in the executing of it, and where there was ſuch a Councell Table to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and to reſolve, and ſuch a perſon to execute, needs muſt the effects of both be high and glorious, ſuitable to the honour, greatneſſe, wiſedome, and power of the high perſons exerciſed in the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of them, and ſo (you ſee) they are.</p>
            <p>LLet no man then for ever hereafter reproach the Chriſtian religion, with the meanneſſe,<note place="margin">Concluſio.</note> or deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cableneſſe of him that was the founder of it. Let no man object unto us the humanity, nor the humility of our Mediatour, when wee ſee for what glorious purpoſes he was content to ſtoope ſo low, and what pretious grace he hath obtained and purchaſed unto his Church in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Let not the <hi>Jewe</hi> ſtumble at the Croſſe of Chriſt, by telling us that we beleeve in a crucified God: nor let the Atheiſt ſtumble at the Cradle of Chriſt by telling us we embrace a Child for our God.<note place="margin">Neſtorius his Blaſphemy.</note> Nor let <hi>Neſtorius</hi> reproach us with our <hi>bimeſtris</hi> aut <hi>trimeſtris Deus,</hi> a God of two or three months old, as hee blaſpemouſly calls him. If the <hi>Child</hi> ſeeme little in your eyes behold the <hi>Sonne,</hi> if the <hi>Cradle</hi> offend you, behold the <hi>Starre,</hi> if the <hi>Croſſe</hi> offend you, behold the <hi>Heavens</hi> without a <hi>Sunne,</hi> and the <hi>Starres</hi> withold their ſhining at the ſpectacle. <hi>And be not faithleſſe but believe, and you ſhall ſee greater things then theſe.</hi> You ſhall ſee <hi>this Sonne of man comming in the clouds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth 25.</note> 
               <hi>with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112840:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:112840:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:112840:23"/> power and great glory.</hi> Now you ſee him in the Cradle, then you ſhall ſee him in a fiery Chariot, riding upon the wings of the wind: now he came in <hi>Virgine,</hi> then hee ſhall come in <hi>Libra,</hi> with a ballance in one hand to weigh the actions of the ſonnes of men, and a two edged ſword in the other, to cut them off, and to be avenged on his enemies, now he came attended with a few fiſhermen, and others of the meaner ſort that followed him: but then he ſhall come attended with thouſands and thouſands of thouſands of Angels, and Arch-Angels: now he came in humility, then he ſhall come in glory; now he came to be judged, but then he ſhall come to judge both quick and dead, yea to judge even them that judged him: &amp; the ſouldiers ſhall looke upon him whom they have pierced;<note place="margin">Zach: 11.</note> and the Jew ſhall looke upon him whom they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and the <hi>Arrians, Eunomians, Ebionites, Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Photinians, Socinians,</hi> and <hi>Mohomitans,</hi> ſhall looke upon him whom they have denyed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and ſhall be confounded, when they ſhall ſee him now armed with power and authority, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on them for their contempts, and injuries done to him and his for his ſake: And thoſe that have confeſſed him, ſhall ſay unto them, by way of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proach and inſultation, <hi>Behold yee deſpiſers and wonder, and periſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.41. Luk: 19.27.</note> And the King ſhall ſay unto them, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to thoſe Rebels in the Goſpell, <hi>Thoſe that would not that I ſhould raigne over them, bring them hither, and ſlay them before my face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12.</note>Oh then <hi>kiſſe the Sonne leſt hee be angry, and ſo ye pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> embrace the Child in the arms of your faith, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112840:23"/> beſt affections,<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> that ſo hereafter he may embrace you in the armes of his mercy, <hi>Infans eſt, noli timere; filius, noli ſpernere:</hi> Behold he is a Child, that you ſhould not be afraid to draw neare unto him; and a Sonne, that you may not diſpiſe him. Let the meditation of the former raiſe in you hope and confidence, and of the latter beget in you feare and reverence, and both together that ſaving comfort, ſound joy, and ſettled peace, that flowes from your reconciliation with God, and your adoption to the honour to become the Sonnes of God, brethren to this Child, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires with this Sonne, of an inheritance in glory, the very end of this his Child-hood, and of this his Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the very end why he was borne to us, and given for us. Lord let him have his end in us, that we may have our fruit in him, even the end of our hopes; the ſalvation of our ſoules in bliſſe, and glory that never ſhall have end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The end of the firſt</hi> Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:112840:24"/>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:112840:24"/>
            <head>COMFORT FROM THE <hi>CRADLE AS</hi> WELL AS from the <hi>Croſse</hi> of CHRIST. <hi>The ſecond</hi> SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ESAIAH 9.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>Vnto us a Child is borne,</l>
                  <l>Vnto us a Sonne is given.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have given you an account of the firſt generall part of the Text inquiring of the perſon, who and what hee is of whom the Prophet ſpeaketh this as he is here repreſented to us under the names and notions of <hi>A Child, A Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tranſitio.</note> and there in I have diſcovered unto you the ſtupendious my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which lyes coucht under theſe two words, and is clearly made out from them, and that is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> really diſtinguiſht natures, united in the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indivi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112840:25"/> perſon of our <hi>Mediatour,</hi> the <hi>Deity</hi> &amp; the <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of the <hi>Son of God,</hi> both made good not only out of the text, but all along throughout the whole courſe of his life, from his birth to his baptiſme, from his baptiſme to his death as in the ſeverall paſſages of them all I have obſerved: In his birth, you had A Cradle for the Child, and a Starre for the Sonne: In his Baptiſme, water for the Child, and a voyce from Heaven for the Sonne, In his paſſion A Croſſe, and A Crowne of thornes, nailes, and a ſpeare, ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, and whippings, and ſtripes for the Child: and thundrings and darkneſſe, and an earth-quake, and rocks cleaving in ſunder, and graves opening, and the veyle of the Temple rent for the Sonne, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally throughout the whole courſe of his life in the ſeverall eminent paſſages of it you ſaw the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord appearing in the cloud, infallible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of the Deity, breaking out through the cloud and veile of his fleſh. I ſhewed you the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all theſe wonders, they were wonderfull things that he was to doe, and therefore not to be tranſacted but by wonderfull means, and by a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull perſon, even by him whoſe name is called <hi>VVonderfull:</hi> And I ſhewed you the friuts iſſuing out of them all. <hi>Glory to God on high, peace on earth below, and towards men good will.</hi> I am now to examine the ſecond generall propoſed,<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note> wherein we are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, what it is which is here affirmed of this Child, and of this Son, and that is laid down in two words more <hi>Is borne, Is given.</hi> The Child is <hi>borne,</hi> but the Sonne is <hi>given.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:112840:25"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Child is borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is was neceſſary that our Mediatour ſhould be made man it is confeſt, and we have ſhewed the reaſons of it: but why A Child? why borne of a woman? why to be conceived in the wombe? this is much more, and ſurely there is more of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in it, which yet we have not diſcovered when the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was created he was made A man, not A child; created, not begotten; A man in full ſtrength and perfection of life, and ſo was excuſed all the impotencies and imperfections of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and infancy. And when the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> came to repaire, and to reſtore what he had loſt, was it not reaſonable, and agreeable to his type that hee ſhould be made a man too in perfect ſtate, ſtature, and perfection of life as the firſt was, and ſo have beene abated all thoſe parts of his ſufferings, and degrees of his humiliation, which in the wombe, and from the wombe in his childhood and infancy hee paſt through, muſt he needs become A Child, be conceived in the wombe, and borne? what was the reaſon of this?</p>
            <p>Yes ſurely there was reaſon for it,<note place="margin">Reaſons why it was neceſſary Chriſt ſhould not onely be made man but borne a Child.</note> nay there was a neceſſity of it, it muſt needs be ſo, and I will give you in three Reaſon for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt concernes the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> in generall.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond concernes the daughters of <hi>Eve</hi> more ſpecially.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And the the third concernes the infants that are borne of them, and iſſue from them both.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:112840:26"/>1 Firſt in reſpect of the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, it was neceſſary that our Mediatour ſhould become a Child, be conceived in the wombe, and borne.<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> That he might begin the cure of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe where our diſeaſe it ſelfe begins, and that is in the very wombe. Behold (ſaies the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>) I was conceived in ſinne, and borne in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. Our bleſſed Lord becomming our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, and undertaking to ſatisfie the juſtice of God for this ſinne, and to cure us of ſo grievous a diſeaſe that layes hold on us in the very wombe is faine to deſcend into the wombe of a daughter of <hi>Eve,</hi> there to take our nature upon him and there to be conceived though without ſinne, and of her to be borne, but without iniquity, a pure birth that ſo by the purity of his humane nature imputed unto us the impurity of ours may be cured and cleanſed, and that by his Originall righteouſneſſe, our originall ſin may be done away. There is beloved if you marke it,<note place="margin">A method ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> in curing the evils we receive from the firſt.</note> and I pray do, for it is well worth your marking, and much comfort ſhall you reap by it when you apprehend it aright) There is I ſay A method obſerved by the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> in curing the evills which we have received from the firſt, it is a methodicall cure, wherein the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> hath trac't the firſt ſtep, by ſtep, and where ever he ſaw that he had wounded us, he prouided to heale us, and prepared for us a remedy proportionable to our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady a ſalve ſuitable to the ſore and proper for the cure of it. To ſhew you this a little more plainly.</p>
            <p>There are three things wherein the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:112840:26"/> hath deadly and deſperately wounded his poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by depraving their natures, this is that which is called Originall ſinne, the corruption and depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our natures from that which we were by creation, by this hee ſtruck us dead in the very wombe, by this we are wicked as ſoone as we are, even before we have done good or evill, wicked in the very roote, becauſe wee have in us a principle of all wickedneſſe, and ſo become children of wrath by nature, miſerable from the very cradle, from the very wombe, even in our conception.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond thing wherein hee undid us was, by breaking Covenant with God in failing in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the condition of it which ſaid thus <hi>fac hoc &amp; vives,</hi> doe this and thou ſhalt live, and ſo brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Commandement in the <hi>mandatory part</hi> of it, be forfeited to himſelfe and his, all that life, and hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pineſſe which upon the condition of obedience was made over to him and them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And the third was by his actuall rebellion againſt God, and poſitive diſobedience, by which he deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately brake the Commandement in the <hi>minatory part</hi> of it, which ſaid, <hi>In quo die comederis morte morie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> in the day that thou eateſt thou ſhalt die the death and ſo made us liable to all the miſeries of this life, and of that which is to come. By his privative diſobedience breaking the holy Comandement, in the <hi>mandatory part</hi> of it he forfeited to himſelfe and us the inheritance of Paradiſe, our right and title to the Kingdome of Heaven, but by his poſitive diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, tranſgreſſing the holy Law and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112840:27"/> in the <hi>minatory part</hi> of it, he hath plung'd us all into the loweſt hell. Now for the relieving of us in all theſe deſperate evils, was our Lord faine to provide for us ſuitable remedies, and to apply each of them to that malady for the cure whereof, it was moſt proper, and ſo he did, though they coſt him deare. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt for the cure of our Originall ſinne he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies his Originall righteouſneſſe, that he may pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſatisfie the juſtice of God for the depravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our natures, the ſinne wherein wee are concei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved and borne, himſelfe is conceived by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that he may begin the cure of our diſeaſe, where our diſeaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, in the very wombe, even thither is hee content to deſcend, and there to take our nature upon him, that in his perſon our natures might be ſanctified, and our birth-ſinne cured and done away.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, for relieving of us in the ſecond of theſe evills, our failing in performance of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant of workes he applyes unto us his active obedience, by which he fulfilled the Law for us in every part and particle of it in the dayes of his fleſh, that ſo by this his obedience imputed unto us he might punctually ſatisfie the Juſtice of God for all our failings, and ſins of omiſſion, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore us againe to our right and title to the Kingdom of heaven our forfeited inheritance.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And for the relieving of us in the third, the tranſgreſſion of the Law and holy Commandement in the <hi>minatory part,</hi> by actuall ſinnes and poſitive
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112840:27"/> diſobedience hee applyes unto us his paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, himſelfe <hi>bearing our ſinnes in his body upon the tree,</hi> and by his death taking off from us that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death that was gone out againſt us: By this his paſſive obedience he hath ſatisfied the law in the <hi>minatory part</hi> of it, and by his active in the <hi>mandatory.</hi> by his paſſive obedience he hath ſatisfied the juſtice of God for all our ſins of Commiſſion, and by his active for all our failings and our ſins of omiſſion, by his paſſive obedience he hath freed us <hi>A poena ſenſus,</hi> from the puniſhment of paine, and by his active <hi>A poena damni,</hi> from the puniſhment of loſſe, by his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive obedience he hath reſcued us out of the jawes of hell, and by his active he hath opened unto us the gate of heaven, his paſſive obedience was ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and his active meritorious: And thus by theſe three parts of his obedience, the obedience of his birth, the obedience of his life, and the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his death, by the obedience of his birth in his incarnation, of his life in his holy converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of his death in his paſſion, hee hath fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for us all righteouſneſſe, he is become unto us <hi>A perfect Saviomr, and hath wrought out for us plentifull redemption.</hi> Had the ſonne of God come downe from Heaven to earth, and here beene made man for us, &amp; taken our nature upon him in a body created, as <hi>Adams</hi> was, and in that body liv'd amongſt us as long as he did, and during all that time by his moſt holy converſation (perfectly fulfilled the Law for us, and performed the condition of the Covenant of workes in our behalfe, yet he had <hi>not wrought out for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112840:28"/> us plentifull redemption,</hi> he had by this his active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, onely fulfilled the Law in the <hi>mandatory part of it,</hi> and ſo ſatisfied the juſtice of God for our ſinnes of omiſſion, but ſtill he had left us open to the juſtice and wrath of God for our ſinnes of Commiſſion, and for our tranſgreſſions of the law in the <hi>minato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of it,</hi> and ſo left us to the curſe of it, even death and damnation. Had hee not onely ſo fulfilled the law for us by his active obedience in the dayes of his life, but in the end thereof laid downe his life for us, and ſhed his blood for the ranſome of our ſoules, yet he had not wrought out for us <hi>plentifull redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> hee had indeed by this his paſſive obedience ſatisfied the juſtice of God for all our ſinnes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion too, and by fulfilling the Law in the <hi>minato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of it,</hi> cleared us of all our tranſgreſſions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt it, but ſtill hee had left us indebted unto God, and in danger of his wrath and juſtice for the ſinne of our nature, our radicall pravitie, and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall corruption in which wee are conceived and borne, but that he might cleare us of this ſin alſo and ſo become unto us a <hi>perfect Saviour and worke out for us Plentifull redemption,</hi> it was neceſſary that hee ſhould be incarnate that in the very wombe hee ſhould take our nature upon him, and be borne of a woman, without ſinne, that ſo by the purity of his humane nature imputed unto us, the impurity of ours might be cured, and that in his perſon, our natures might be ſanctified in the wombe, and from the wombe.</p>
            <p>And ſo by grace derived from theſe three parts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:112840:28"/> in the obedience of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured of all the evill wee receaved from the firſt, by the merit of his incarnation in his holy birth by his active obedience in his holy life, and of his paſſive obedience in his bitter death and paſſion hee hath, <hi>fulfilled for us all righteouſneſſe, he is become unto us a perfect Saviour, and hath wrought out for us plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full redemption.</hi> And this was the firſt reaſon why it was neceſſary that our Mediator ſhould not onely be made man, but borne a child.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon of this part and paſſage in the obedience of our Mediatour, and of this ſo low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of his humiliation, reſpects the Woman, more eſpecially even <hi>Eve</hi> with all her daughters, for their ſakes more peculiarly, and unto them, and of them was he borne, that by his birth hee might repaire them in a loſſe, and recover them out of a danger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which beyond and aboue the man they had caſt themſelves by being <hi>firſt in the tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you heedfully obſerve the ſtory of the fall compared with other Scriptures commenting upon it, you will finde it to be ſo:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> if you read but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe made againſt her, and the doome pronounc't upon her at the day of her tryall, you will finde a heavier charge againſt her, and a greater burthen laid upon her, then upon <hi>Adam</hi> was laid: but wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that, the Scripture upon which this reaſon is grounded is that famous place of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.16. <hi>verſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1.2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Yet nevertheleſse through child-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſhe ſhall be ſavd if they continue in Faith and Charity with holineſſe and ſobroetie,</hi> which becauſe it is a very
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112840:29"/> intricate Scripture one of thoſe which are hard to be underſtood, and ſo generally miſtaken by moſt men, ſo few have attained to the true meaning of it, I will take ſome paines to examine it, and to finde; it out both for my own and others ſatisfaction which that I may doe, I muſt intreat you to looke back with me to 2. or 3. verſes going before, there you ſhall finde the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had laid 2 heavy yokes upon her, <hi>Silence</hi> and <hi>Subiection,</hi> V. 11. And that you may know what ſilence he meanes, in the next verſe hee interprets himſelfe and tells you he meanes ſilence as tis put in oppoſition to teaching, or publique preaching. <hi>I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not a woman to teach</hi> (though I ſee not but by the grounds upon which moſt men take upon them to teach now adaies ſhe hath as good a licence to teach as any of them all, and that is (meerely the inward calling) or at leaſt a conceipt of it, but S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> that had reaſon to knowe their gifts of ability well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and their deſire to exerciſe them in the Church yet directly ſilences them as to this intent, ſhe that preacht ſuch falſe doctrine to her husband as whereby ſhe had undone us all, he thinks it fit ſhe ſhould be ſilence't from ever preaching more. <hi>I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not a woman to teach, but let her be ſilent.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> 
               <hi>Subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I permit not the woman to uſurp authority over the man,</hi> in the ſame verſe, if ſhe doe tis uſurpation, ſhee hath no right ſo to doe. Therefore let her be <hi>ſilent,</hi> and let her be <hi>ſubiect,</hi> v. 11.12. But verſe 14. the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſhews the reaſon why the Lord laid this hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vy burthen upon her, and that was the deepneſſe of her guilt in the matter of the firſt and great tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112840:29"/> 
               <hi>For Adam was not in the tranſgreſſion, but Eve being deceived was in the tranſgreſſion,</hi> that is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely nothing ſo deeply as ſhee was, hee was in it but as acceſſary ſhe was the principall, for firſt ſhee ſeduced him &amp; ſo became an Agent for Satan to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with her husband to doe that which himſelfe was confident he could never have perſwaded him too. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, She was <hi>firſt in the tranſgreſsion.</hi> A grievous aggravation, if rightly conſidered, for the meaning of it is ſhe was <hi>firſt in the tranſgreſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> not only becauſe ſhe firſt gave her conſent to Satan tempting her, nor becauſe ſhe tempted her husband to doe the like, who of himſelfe had no ſuch thoughts nor deſires that we read of till ſhe ſuggeſted them, but ſhee was firſt in the tranſgreſſion, becauſe ſhe did firſt actually eat of the forbidden fruit without the conſent of her hurband, or knowledge either, for ſure enough the iubtle Serpent watcht the advantage of ſuch an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to attempt her in the abſence of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band whom he might well imagine would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented her tranſgreſsion and given her better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, &amp; what a grievous errour was this in her to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture upon ſuch a fact of ſo infinite conſequence as this was upon which depended the everlaſting weale or woe of her ſelfe and all her poſterity after her; without the knowledge or conſent of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who might have given her better counſell, and whoſe adviſe in all reaſon ſhe ſhould have deſired, but ſhe ſtaid not for that ſhe hearkned to the Serpent promiſing high things unto her to enſue upon her eating and ſhe believed him, and ſo without ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112840:30"/> him with it, ſhe eat of it, <hi>ſhee was firſt in the tranſgreſsion,</hi> this as it was the aggravation of her ſin ſo it might be ſome extenuation to <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, who did therein but ſecond what ſhe had done before, for by her eating, the Covenant was broken, the law tranſgreſſed, and though <hi>Adam</hi> had not eaten at all yet ſhe had done enough to undoe us all at leaſt her ſelfe and all her daughters which were involved in the tranſgreſsion with her and with whom they all ſtood and fell;</p>
            <p>Vpon theſe aggravations the Lord doth not only lay upon her theſe burthens before mentioned, but the Apoſtle in this Text which I have under hand intimates a greater danger, which ſhe had caſt her ſelfe into then all they amount unto, even into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her of periſhing everlaſtingly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eve</hi> by her tranſgreſſon caſt all her daughters into farre greater danger then <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> did his Sonnes.</note> what elſe meanes this adverſative here in the Text <hi>nevertheleſſe. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe (through child-bearing ſhe ſhall be ſaved.</hi> It ſhews plainly that if God had not found out a remedy for her, if God of his goodneſſe had not provided a meanes whereby ſhe might be relieved in this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous caſe ſhe could not have beene ſaved.</p>
            <p>Hence hath ariſen the queſtion whether <hi>Eve</hi> were ſaved or no, and from that another touching the ſtate of all her ſexe for her ſake, the opening of this Text ſhall cleare them both.</p>
            <p>That both <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> our firſt parents were ſaved, we nothing doubt, yea <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iphanius</hi> have recorded it that after <hi>Adam</hi> had finiſhed his daies on earth, and was returned to his duſt from whence he was taken, he was buried in mount <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vary</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:112840:30"/> in the very place whereabout 4000 yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Croſſe was ſet on which <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was crucified. A wonderfull providence (if true) <hi>Vt primus virtutem ſanguinis Chriſti ſentiret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen.</note> 
               <hi>qui primus peccati author fuerit, that he might firſt taſt the power and vertue of Chriſts blood which was firſt cauſe of ſhedding it</hi> and what fitter objects for the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> on which to ſhew his power to ſave,<note place="margin">Epiphan.</note> then thoſe very perſons on whom Satan had uſed all his skill, and power to deſtroy. But the queſtion is not ſo much whether they were ſaved, as how, and this not ſo much of the Man as of the Woman for the reaſons before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. And the Apoſtle tells you in this Text, how, he ſaies it ſhall be <hi>by Child-bearing. Yet nevertheleſſe by or through Child-bearing ſhe ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what child-bearing he here meanes is ſtill the <hi>Quaere,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt Authors that I have conſulted in this matter (and I have conſulted not a few) concieve it to be underſtood of theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Of the ſore paine and travaile which women indure in chid-bearing, which being laid upon them as a puniſhment for this their tranſgreſſion by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during it with patience in the acknowledgment of their offence that brought it upon them they make ſome amends for that which they had done amiſſe, and ſatisfaction for their tranſgreſſion, ſo <hi>Cornelius à Lapide</hi> and thoſe of his ſtrayne.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, Others extend it not only to bearing of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but eſpecially to breeding up of Children in the feare of God, and nurture of the Lord, becauſe in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:112840:31"/> the next words tis ſaid (<hi>if they continue in faith and love with holineſſe, &amp; ſobrietie,</hi> which they underſtand as required of the Children which they beare bred up in theſe gratious waies by their care, and ſo by this meanes they ſhall be ſaved; So <hi>Danaeus</hi> &amp; others both equally miſtaken, neither in the one nor in the other have they hit the Apoſtles meaning,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Tim. 16.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted and cleered.</note> examine it a litle and you ſhall ſee whether they have or no.</p>
            <p>For if the extraordinary paines which women endure be a kinde of amends, and ſatisfaction for their extraordinary tranſgreſſion, then what doe we by this doctrine but eſtabliſh a Purgatory, and ſet out a way of ſatisfying for ſin and meriting life and ſalvation by doing and ſuffering? Moreover, if child bearing in this ſenſe be the ſoveraigne remedy of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering that ſexe out of the danger they have brought upon themſelves by that great tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the meanes whereby they ſhall be ſaved, what ſhall become of the barren wombe that beares not, or of maidens that knowe not man? Surely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account the caſe of Harlots, and Strumpets were better then theirs; but to finde out the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles meaning, here we muſt finde out another child-bearing, ſuch as all the daughters of <hi>Eve</hi> have a ſhare in, ſuch as in which the barren as well as the bearing wombe, the maiden that never knew man as well as the married wife hath an equall intereſt.</p>
            <p>This place therefore may be beſt expounded by another place of the ſame <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3:16.</note> 
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. Where the Apoſtle diſcourſing of the promiſe of God to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. Gen.</hi> 22.18. <hi>In thy ſeed ſhall all the nations of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112840:31"/> earth be bleſſed,</hi> excellently obſerves: <hi>This is not ſpoken to his ſeeds as of many, but as of one unto thy ſeed which is Chriſt:</hi> By the like analogy, as <hi>Paul</hi> here interprets <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo wil I interpret <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſaith not in this place the woman ſhall be ſaved by bearing of Children as ſpeaking of many, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>through her child-birth, or child-bearing as meaning one,</hi> which one is <hi>Chriſt</hi> the very Child in my Text, the <hi>Child Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if this be ſo why was not the mentioning of the Child enough, by the Child ſhe ſhall be ſaved,<note place="margin">It is uſuall with the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> to put the abſtract for the concrete, <hi>Child-bearing</hi> for the <hi>Child-borne,</hi> or the child which ſhe ſhould beare</note> what need any mention of the bearing of it <hi>by Child-bearing? ſhe ſhall be ſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes there is ſomething in that too, there is an emphaſis in that, even by the bearing of the Child doth the woman gaine not only honour and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation above the man, but reparation in her loſſe and comfort after her fall ſuitable to the danger ſhe had fallen into<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by this her Child-birth ſhee receives more grace from him, and hath a neerer relation to him and intereſt in the Saviour of the world then the man hath, and this the Scripture takes ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall notice of, and often mentions for her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Semen mulieris, the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall breake the Serpents head,</hi> not ſo of the man, he did not ſo much as ſhare with her in this honour. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>In the fulneſſe of time God ſent his Sonne made of a woman,</hi> not of a man, the firſt woman was made of a man, now by a contrary way of generation, this man, this bleſſed Child in whom all the nations of the earth are bleſſed, was made of a woman, even of one of the daughters of <hi>Eve, the Virgin Mary:</hi> ſo that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112840:32"/> as in the firſt <hi>Eve</hi> conceiving ſinne all the whole ſex and race of her daughters miſcarried, ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Eve</hi> (as I may ſay) conceiving in her wombe, and bearing in her body the Saviour of the world,<note place="margin">sA the firſt <hi>Eve</hi> conceiving ſin brought forth death, So the ſecond <hi>Eve</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour brought forth life.</note> they are all repar'd, and reſtor'd againe. As ſhee (by being firſt in the tranſgreſſion, caſt all her daughters into a more deſperate condition then <hi>Adam</hi> did his ſonnes, ſo God found out a more ſoveraigne remedy for her by which ſhe receives more grace from Chriſt, and challenges a neerer relation to and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Saviour of the world then he can claime: from her ſubſtance, did he take that fleſh which hee offered up in ſacrifice to God for us, from her body did he take that blood which he ſhed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the world, he could truly call a woman his mother, but no man living his Father, as <hi>Adam</hi> once ſaid to <hi>Eve, Thou art fleſh of my fleſh, and bone of my bone,</hi> ſo could the ſecond <hi>Eve,</hi> in whom all the daughters of the firſt are repair'd and reſtor'd, ſay to to the Saviour of the world, <hi>Thou art fleſh of my fleſh, and bone of my bone,</hi> unto all the which relations the man is a ſtranger, and ſhares not with her in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of them.</p>
            <p>See how the goodneſſe of God for the comfort of that ſexe againſt this their grievous fall hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a remedy ſuitable to their maladie, a meaſure of conſolation anſwerable to their dejection, a ground of hope agreeable to their feares &amp; doubts, a reparation proportionable to their loſſe, if they were firſt in the tranſgreſſion, they are likewiſe firſt in being inſtrumentall in the meanes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112840:32"/> if they were deepeſt in the guilt of the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rication they were faireſt for the meanes of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. <hi>Through Child-bearing ſhe ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this cauſe was this child the ſeed the woman. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. Made of a Woman, <hi>Gai.</hi> 4, 4. Borne of a Woman, <hi>Math.</hi> 1. and that ſexe may ſay after a more peculiar manner then the man may, <hi>Vnto us,</hi> yea of us, and for us, <hi>this Child is borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That other condition which followes in this Text, <hi>If they continue in faith, and love with holineſſe, and ſobriety,</hi> is not to be referred to the children that are to be borne of the Woman, but to the woman her ſelfe, upon whom theſe duties are eſpecially charged as cautions or preſervatives to keepe her from ever falling into the like ſinne againe, as you ſhall heare anon: but that they are not to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood here as charg'd upon her children is cleare by this, that they are charged as conditions upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhe is to be ſaved, now if to this intent the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions here mentioned be charged upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then by this doctrine may Parents be ſaved by the holineſſe and righteouſneſſe of their children which is cleane contrary to the exact juſtice of God revealed in Scripture which ſaith <hi>iuſtus ſua fide vivet, the iuſt ſhall live by his owne faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides we have knowne many gracious women which have done their beſt in this way to bring up their children in faith, and love, in holineſſe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, which yet have not proved ſuch, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe we could inſtance in ſome carnall, lewd, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112840:33"/> ungodly women, whoſe children have proved graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in faith with love, &amp;c. And yet neither hath the graciouſneſſe of theſe profited, nor the graceleſneſſe of the other prejudic't to the ſaving or not ſaving of their mothers that bare them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this charge in this place referres not to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are borne but to the woman that beares them.</p>
            <p>All the difficulty will be how we ſhall reconcile this ſeeming incongruity betweene the 2 pronouns <hi>ſhee</hi> and <hi>they, ſhee</hi> ſhall bee ſaved if <hi>they</hi> continue, how can theſe two in grammaticall conſtruction be refer'd to the ſame as underſtood of the ſame perſon or perſons?</p>
            <p>For ſatisfying of this doubt conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt divers Greek copies have it in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar number, ſo <hi>Muſculas,</hi> and ſo <hi>Theophilact</hi> reads it ſo <hi>Danaeus,</hi> and others, <hi>ſi permanſerit,</hi> if ſhee continue, not they, and if that reading be currant there is no farther queſtion at all in the matter.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But be it ſo, that the latter Pronoune &amp; Verbe be of the plurall number, it is uſuall with the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews to joyne ſingulars and pluralls together,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Dii creavit</hi> in which is the myſtery of the Trinity.</note> in the two very firſt words of the holy Bible, you have ſuch an expreſſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3 But that which is ſatisfactory beyond excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this that the firſt pronoune <hi>ſhe,</hi> though it be of the ſingular number, yet is of plurall ſignification, <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men multitudinis,</hi> a name of multitude, ſuch as <hi>Turba ruunt, collectivum á collective</hi> pronounce, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112840:33"/> in it not only <hi>Eve,</hi> but all woman kinde, all her whole ſexe and race deſcended from her, and ſo is aequivalent and of as large extent as <hi>they</hi> in the next word, <hi>ſhe,</hi> that is <hi>Eve</hi> with all her daughters, all her ſexe, all the whole race of womankind deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſhall be ſaved, <hi>If they continue in the faith and loue, with holineſſe and ſobriety.</hi> And that this charge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the woman more peculiarly it further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the ſuitablenes of it to the ſin by which ſhe had tranſgreſt, the foure duties here enjoyned being directly oppoſite to the foure ſinnes by which in her firſt and great tranſgreſſion ſhe had offended, her firſt ſinne was unbeliefe, God had ſaid <hi>in the day that ſhe did eat of that fruit, ſhe ſhould dye,</hi> the Devill told her <hi>ſhe ſhould not dye at all,</hi> and ſhe believes him rather then God, ſhe was an unbelieving ſoule, therefore the firſt duty charg'd upon her is <hi>Faith, if they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in faith,</hi> the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> fin was in violating the law of love which ſhe ow'd both to God and to her husband, ſhe ſlighted them both and adher'd to the Serpent as her better friend, and therefore the next duty charg'd upon her is <hi>Love,</hi> if ſhe continue in love. Her third ſinne was againſt the rules of holineſſe, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed her ſelfe by touching and taſting that which being forbidden her, was to her polluted, and ſo by her grievous ſinne drew not only upon her ſelfe, but upon all hers, corruption of nature, which like the leproſie of <hi>Gehazi,</hi> cleaves to them &amp; their poſterity for ever: and therefore the third duty enjoynd &amp; charg'd upon her is <hi>holineſſe.</hi> Laſtly her fourth ſinne was intemperance, in that all the variety of the fruits
<pb facs="tcp:112840:34"/> in the Paradiſe of God which he had ſo graciouſly and bountifully allowd her, not only for neceſſity but for delight too, yet would not ſerve her turne, but whereas there were but two trees reſerv'd) her luxurious appetite muſt needs glut it ſelfe with them too, and therefore the fourth duty charged upon her is <hi>temperance or ſobrietie if they continue in faith and love with holineſse and ſobrietee,</hi> by all which du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties directly oppoſite to the ſins whereby ſhe had tranſgreſt, the Apoſtle doth not onely put them in minde of thoſe ſinnes, that in remembrance of them they may be humbled and caution'd againſt the like ſinnes hereafter: but alſo admoniſheth them by the ſtudious and carefull practiſe of the contrary duties to make amends for their former folly, and to take a holy revenge of themſelves for their paſt error whereby they had ſo grievouſly offended.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſecond reaſon enforcing the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the child-birth in my Text in reference to the woman and all women kinde, I have beene ſomething large in opening this Scripture upon which this reaſon is grounded in regard of the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of it, and for juſtifying this interpretation and cleering it of thoſe obje &amp; ions which might ſeeme to queſtion it, wherein I hope I have given you ſome reaſonable ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third reaſon for which it was neceſſary this child ſhould be borne reſpects infants, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren more peculiarly: for infants ſakes did he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an infant, for childrens ſakes was hee content become a child; that by his <hi>birth</hi> hee might merit
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112840:34"/> for them their <hi>New-birth,</hi> hee was borne, that they might be borne againe. That from his very concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and incarnation they might draw virtue, and derive grace to their ſpirituall regeneration, and in his perſon their natures might be ſanctified in the very wombe: That <hi>in him</hi> the Lord might become not only the God of beleevers, but <hi>of their ſeed alſo,</hi> that the promiſe made to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by this means might be made good, &amp; they made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of receiving it, though as yet they knew him not, nor their right hand from their left. And this part of his humiliation (as for this end it was moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, ſo) for our comfort it was not obſcurely fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed and preacht to the world by the Prophets of old. In the 49. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and the 10. <hi>verſe,</hi> we have a famous and ancient propheſie to this purpoſe. <hi>The ſcepter ſhall not depart from Iudah, nor a Law-giver from between his feet till Shiloh come.</hi> It is cleere by all the circumſtances in the Text, and by the fulfilling of the propheſie ſince (which is the beſt interpretation of it) that by this <hi>Shiloh</hi> is meant none other but the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of the world, but why <hi>Shiloh,</hi> rather then the <hi>Meſſiah, Emanuel,</hi> or any other of his names by which he is in ſcripture made knowne unto us, why doth the Patriarch propheſie of him under ſo ſtrange a name? ſurely there is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in it, and if you conſult the Hebrew it will give you ſome light to the finding of it out. This word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with very little alteration either in ſenſe or ſound refers to a word,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Shiliah.</note> which in the originall ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies that part in a child-bearing woman which is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112840:35"/> called <hi>ſecundina,</hi> the <hi>After-birth,</hi> that filme which containes the Child in the womde after it is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and wherein it is nouriſhed by the navell untill it be ripened for the birth, ſo that in this expreſſion there is a double figure; firſt by a <hi>Metonimy,</hi> naming the veſſell containing for that which is contained in it, by <hi>Shiloh</hi> here is ſignified a man child <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſonne and then by a ſynecdoche uſing a word more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall for that which is more particular and eminent in that kinde, by this childe is meant none other but the <hi>holy Child Ieſus,</hi> the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> that was to come in whom this propheſie was evidently fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. This is that then which in this propheſie is ſo remarkable, and ſpeaks home to out purpoſe, That this holy <hi>Prophet,</hi> and <hi>Patriarch</hi> propheſiing of this great <hi>Prince</hi> the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and preaching to the world the Saviour thereof, hee doth not ſhew you Chriſt upon the Croſſe ſuffering for our ſinnes, nor Chriſt in the pulpit preaching to the world the doctrine of ſalvation; nor Chriſt working miracles, going about and doing good, though all theſe were neceſſary parts of his, obedience and performances of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his Mediatorſhip reſpectively, but hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of Chriſt in <hi>Shiloh,</hi> he points at Chriſt in <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh,</hi> he ſends you to Chriſt in <hi>Shiloh</hi> to Chriſt in the wombe, to Chriſt in his incarnation, to Chriſt in his conception, that you may knowe that you derive grace and vertue, not only from Chriſt crucified, but from Chriſt borne and incarnate, not onley from his death, but from his birth too, not onely
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:112840:35"/> from his blood which he ſhed for you, but even from the holy ſeed of which his body was formed for you not only from the Croſſe of Chriſt, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from his cradle too, not only from his paſſion and crucifixion, but from his conception, and incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Hence you ſhall obſerve that the holy pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of our bleſſed Lords life and death, are as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and punctuall in giving you an account of his conception, and incarnation, as of his death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, conſult but the beginning of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell for the one, and of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Lukes</hi> for the other, &amp; you ſhall finde it to be ſo. And the <hi>Apoſtolicall Creed</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches you and tells you, that it is not ſufficient that you knowe and believe that he was crucified for you under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> but alſo that he <hi>was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for you by the holy Ghoſt, and born of the Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> That the Infants even as yet unborne may have cauſe to praiſe him who out of a tender regard to them was content to take their nature and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon him in the wombe, that he might cure them: What once the Lord by way of reproach ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt his unthankfull people. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. that may he by way of magnifying his compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward theſe little ones moſt ſuitably apply to them word for word, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Thy Father was an Amorite, and thy Mother an Hittite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>And in thy nativitie when thou waſt borne, thy navill was not cut, thou waſt not waſht with water to ſoften thee, thou waſt not ſalted with ſalt, nor ſwadled with clothes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>None eye pitied thee to doe any of theſe unto thee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112840:36"/> for to have compaſsion upon thee, but thou waſt caſt out in the open field to the contempt of thy perſon in the day that thou waſt borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>And when I paſſed by thee I ſaw thee polluted in thine owne blood, And I ſaid unto thee when thou waſt in thy blood I ſaid thou ſhalt live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Now when I paſſed by thee, I had compaſsion on thee I ſpred my skirt over thee, and covered thy nakedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>I waſhed thee with water, yea I waſhed away thy blood frous thee, I annointed thee with oyle, and I cloathed thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was their caſe, and this was their cure, and ſuch was his love to them and his compaſſion on them, that to the end he might effect it, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent not only to be made man but to become a child too for their ſakes. And this is the third Reaſon why. Unto us, and unto them this Child is borne.</p>
            <div type="uses">
               <head>The Vſes.</head>
               <p>ANd now whar uſe ſhall we make of this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſurely very great, It is of great uſe in the Church of God, well-nigh all the errors that men have runne into concerning Infants have procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the ignorance of this Goſpell truth, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the grace and vertue which we derive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from this part in the obedience of Chriſt, and degree of his humiliation, his <hi>conception,</hi> and <hi>incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt therefore it is of uſe for ſatisfaction of doubtfull minds in that <hi>Quaere</hi> which theſe times have made more queſtionable then ever (as indeed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112840:36"/> they have done all the other ordinances in the Church of Chriſt) concerning the lawfulnes of the baptizing of Infants? Who will doubt it when hee is ſufficiently inform'd what grace and vertue they receive from the incarnation,<note place="margin">The ground of baptizing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants.</note> and birth of the <hi>holy Child Ieſus?</hi> And that the very end why hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Child and was conceived in the womb, was to merit it for them? Are they capable of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conveyed unto them from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in their very conception, before they have done good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and are they not capable of the grace merited for them and derived unto them from the ſecond untill they come to be of 14. or 15. yeares of age? or if they be why ſhould we deny unto them the ſeale of that covenant the grace whereof wee doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them? Nay upon this ground I dare affirme that if it were poſſible, it were lawfull to baptize a childe in the very wombe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the knowledge of this truth is of uſe for confutation of the uncharitable doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> concerning infants dying without baptiſme,<note place="margin">The ſtate of children dying without bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> which cruelly condemnes all ſuch (though not to the loweſt hell) yet to a place belonging to it which they call <hi>Limbus infantum,</hi> the <hi>Limbus</hi> of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, a hard ſentence, ſome of the Fathers likewiſe of better repute in the Church, have puzzeld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and been miſtaken in this point, ſome of them condemning infants thus dying <hi>ad poenam damni,</hi> though excuſing them from <hi>Poena ſenſus,</hi> that is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving them of the happineſſe and joyes of heaven, though not condemning them to the paines of Hell
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:112840:37"/> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> laies upon them <hi>poenam mitiſſimam,</hi> ſome moſt gentle puniſhment, but what that is dares not determine, <hi>Prudentius</hi> goes a middle way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene both, the happineſſe of heaven hee will not allow them, nor dares hee condemne them to the paines of hell, but hath found out for them a third place betweene both theſe, and that is the new hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven, and the new earth which ſhall be created when theſe ſhall be diſſolv'd, thus have they wandred in their own fancies, and framd to themſelves divers conceipts in their own imaginations concerning theſe little ones, but all without a guide, and without a ground, and all this becauſe all this while they ſaw not this little one herein my Text, or at leaſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered not the maine reaſon why he became ſuch a one, nor the vertue and the grace which theſe little ones they ſpeake of derive from him, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar from this degree of his humiliation, his concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and incarnation, as the cure of their originall ſinne and ſanctification of their natures, their rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and new birth, all which (had meanes and opportunity for it been afforded) ſhould and ought in the laver of regeneration to have been ſealed up unto them, in the want of which and not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of it, let us know for our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort that the grace of Almightie God is not ſo tied to his outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, as that he may not &amp; often doth ſave with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and may when he pleaſe diſpenſe with the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or omiſſion of it, though we may not,
<q>
                     <l>Baptiſmus ſignum eſt non cauſa ſalutis</l>
                     <l>Contempſiſſe nefas, ſed caruiſſe minùs.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:112840:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baptiſme is the ſigne, but not the cauſe of ſalvation, it is the contempt, not the want of it that is ſo dangerous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is of uſe for conſolation to tenderhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted parents mourning over their children either ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne,<note place="margin">Of Children ſtill borne.</note> or called out of the world before they were waſht in the Laver of regeneration: Let them not give them for loſt, nor mourne for them as men without hope when they ſee the grace derived from the incarnation of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt takes hold of them in the very wombe, and reaches to their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conception.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Laſtly, it is of uſe for reprehenſion of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and uncharitableneſſe of ſome men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the baſe opinion they have entertained of <hi>abortive births,</hi> eſteeming no more nor better of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then of ſo much earth diggd out of the ground, yea of ſo much carrion and therefore have denied them Chriſtian buriall, or any other ordinary reſpect,<note place="margin">Of abortive births.</note> which if not in <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> yet at leaſt in <hi>Humanity</hi> were due to the children of <hi>Adam.</hi> Let ſuch knowe that even thoſe abortives if they were once formed and quickned in the wombe, and had that ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into them, whereby they were diſtinguiſhed from vegetatives and ſenſitives, they were capable of that grace which in his conception this child in my Text hath merited for them. It is worth our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to conſider in what tearmes the Covenant runnes. <hi>I will be thy God and the God of thy ſeed:</hi> not of thy of-ſpring, nor of thy poſterity, nor of thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but of thy <hi>Seed,</hi> intimating that even in the womb as ſoone as they have a being, while they are
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:112840:38"/> but yet as ſeed the Lord takes them into Covenant with him and ownes them for his own.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the benefits which we reap by the birth of this bleſſed Child, theſe the fruits and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages accrewing to the Church by this part of his obedience, this degree of his humiliation, his incarnation. And it ſhall be our wiſdome to learne, &amp; much for our comfort, diſtinctly to knowe Chriſt borne, Chriſt crucified, Chriſt dead, Chriſt raiſed, Chriſt aſcended, Chriſt glorified, Chriſt in all the parts of his obedience, and degrees of his humiliation, and exaltation, and to diſcerne what particular grace, &amp; comfort each part and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in it doth peculiarly afford, and to apply it to that part of our diſeaſe and ſpirituall defect in our ſoules for the cure whereof it is moſt proper. As there is no wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d given unto us by the diſobedience of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> but there is found in the obedience of the ſecond a cure proper for it, this when you are able to diſcover and ſutably to apply then have you learned Chriſt crucified indeed, when you can ſee in his originall righteouſnes, the cure of your origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne, in his active obedience, your fulfilling of the law in the precept or mandatory part of it, in his paſſive obedience your ſatisfaction of the law in the curſe or minatory part of it, when you can ſee in his apprehenſion your diſmiſſion, in his condemnation, your abſolution, in his ſtripes, your healing, in his death, your life in his reſurrection and aſcention, your glorification, all theſe are impli'd in the paralel between the two <hi>Adams, Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>As by one mans
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:112840:38"/> diſobedience many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous,</hi> when you are able to compare theſe two together, and to ſuit the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell in all the parts of it, <hi>As and ſo,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> have <hi>you learn'd Chriſt crucified aright,</hi> It is ſomething to know Chriſt crucified in groſſe, <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners,</hi> this is ſomething it gives the <hi>Fisith of adherence,</hi> but when you are able to know this more diſtinctly; to take his obedience, his merits, his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe into parts, to diſcover what grace, what comfort, each part doth peculiarly afford, and then ſuitably to apply it to that part of your ſpirituall diſeaſe for the cure whereof it is intended; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> does the ſoule take in full ſatisfaction, then is it confirm'd with ſtrong coſolation.</p>
               <p>We read in the 4. Chap. of the 2. of Kings, how <hi>Eleſha</hi> going to raiſe the <hi>Shunamits</hi> child from death to life, <hi>he went up the bed where the child lay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Kings 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and hee ſtretcht himſelfe upon the child, and laid his face to the childs face, his eyes to the childs eyes, his hands to the childs hands,</hi> and applied himſelfe unto it part by part, and ſo the fleſh of the child grew warme, and he <hi>neeſed</hi> 7 <hi>times and revived,</hi> ſo wee if wee can apply our ſelves to this child in my text part by part by a particular and diſtinct knowledge and application of his righteouſneſſe, merits, and obedience to our ſoules, not the child, but we which are dead in ſins and treſpaſſes by vertue and grace derived from him ſhall revive and live.</p>
               <p>And this is the peculiar grace which wee receive from this part of his obedience, his incarnation even
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:112840:39"/> the ſanctification of our natures in and from the wombe and the healing of them of that deadly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe which we bring into the world with us our ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſin. And now when you underſtand this aright, when you conſider what ineſtimable grace we derive from this degree of our Lords humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when you underſtand what infinite benefits he hath purchaſed unto his Church by this part of his obedience; you will the leſſe wonder at the wonder. The wonder indeed of wonders, THE INCAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATION OF THE LORD OF GLORY, <hi>God manifeſted in the fleſh.]</hi> That he which was in the forme of God, and thought it no robbery to be equall with God, yet ſhould thus annihilate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as to make himſelfe of no reputation for our ſakes, &amp; ſtoop ſo low to doe us good? that he whom the heaven of heavens is not able to containe ſhould be content to be impriſoned in the narrow circle &amp; darkſome cell of a Virgins wombe? that hee which was the Prince of heaven ſitting in ſtate and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty at the right hand of his father, ſhould as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant ſuck the breaſts of his Mother, that he ſhould ſtrip himſelfe of his Robes of glory, to be wrapt in ſwadling cloathes, and come downe from thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Heaven to cry in a Cradle? No marvell then if among all the paſſages of his humiliation the Church celebrate this as a wonder of wonders well worthy a roome in her deſpiſed Liturgie, <hi>When thou tookeſt upon thee to deliver man thou didſt not abhor the Virgins Wombe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:112840:39"/>
               <p>And ſo we leave the <hi>Child borne</hi> in the armes of his Mother,<note place="margin">Tranſitio.</note> while in the next place wee conſider a while the gift of the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnto us a Sonne is given.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The words at the firſt ſound of them ſpeake a great mercy from God,<note place="margin">The ſecond branch of the ſecond generall.</note> and beſpeake a proportionable meaſure of thankfulneſſe from man in returne of it, with what earneſt ſuits have holy men and women importun'd the Lord, that hee would be pleaſed to give them a ſonne? With what ioy and thankfulnes have they received him, when hee was given? <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Sarah, Hannah</hi> the <hi>Shunamite</hi> to both theſe bear witneſſe upon record, why behold of this mercy are we all partakers in a more eminent manner then all or any of them were, For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnto us a Sonne is given.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two things which doe wonderfully mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the grace and bounty of Almighty God in this marvellous gift beſtowed upon the ſonnes of men.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The greatneſſe of it, It is a Sonne.</item>
                  <item>2. The Freeneſſe of it, It is a gift.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The greatneſſe of it. Of all the good &amp; perfect gifts that have beene from above, or that ever came downe from the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> there was never a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny like this the gift of the ſon of that Father, what could the Lord have parted with, or given unto us that was more deare unto him, then his owne ſonne out of his own boſome? it was more then if hee had <hi>Given us the heathen for our inheritance, or the uttermoſt arts of the earth for our poſſeſsion,</hi> we read of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:112840:40"/> that <hi>When he aſcended up on high,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>hee led captivity captive, and gave gifts unto men,</hi> but how great a gift was that wherein he was given, which gave thoſe gifts? in whom all thoſe gifts are included, from whom they are all derived. in him <hi>are hidden all the treaſures of wiſdome and godlineſſe, and out of his fulneſſe we all receave grace for grace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. Joh. 1.</note> when God gave unto us his Sonne, with him he gave us all his righteouſneſſe merits, and obedience, with all the benefits by them purchaſed unto the Church, in him hee gave us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of our ſoules and bodies, iuſtification, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, reconciliation, to God, remiſſion of ſins, and life everlaſting, <hi>For of him and from him and by him are they all to him be the glory of all for ever &amp; ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing in this gift which magnifies the bounty of our heavenly father is the Freeneſſe of it, it is a gift, <hi>donum gratuitum,</hi> a Free gift. Nothing did the Lord ſee in us which might promerit it, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could he expect fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us in compenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it, it proceeded meerly from a principle within himſelf, pure love, meere mercy, free grace, that he beſtowed upon us this free gift. <hi>He ſent redempteon to his people, In the fulneſſe of time God ſent his Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm, Gal. 4.4.</note> wee could not fetch him <hi>who ſhould aſcend up to heaven to fetch him thence?</hi> We did not ſo much as deſire him to come, we were not ſo ſenſible of our own miſery as to look after him, we did not know that we ſtood in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny need of him, but the Lord did, and therefore out of his meere compaſſion he <hi>Sent</hi> him, out of his meer bounty he <hi>gave</hi> Him, <hi>The Sonne was given.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now out of theſe two, the greatneſſe of this gift
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:112840:40"/> and the freeneſſe of it we will infallibly conclude theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, That the Lord loves the ſonnes of men, what greater evidence could be given of it then this that he hath given his own ſonne to be borne for them, and to dye for them? When <hi>Abraham</hi> did but offer to offer up his ſonne in ſacrifice to God, God bid him hold his hand, goe no farther, the very offer of it was evidence enough of unfeined love to him that commanded it, <hi>Now (ſaith the Lord) I know that thou loveſt me.</hi> Gen. 25.</p>
               <p>If that were evidence cleere enough of mans love to God how much ſtronger muſt it needs bee of Gods far greater love to man that did not only offer to offer up his ſonne, but offered him up indeed a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for their ranſome? No marvayle if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> reporting this ſet it forth with a note of admiration. <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his onely begotten ſonne to the end that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh but have life everlaſting.</hi> Thoſe foure circumſtances in that Text, <hi>tantus, tantillos, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> and <hi>tanti.</hi> That ſuch a high Majeſtie as the Lord is, ſhould ſo value ſuch wormes as we are, as to give for us ſuch a price as he did, to redeem us out of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and thraldome by the death of his owne ſonne, doe rayſe this his love to ſuch a heighth as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the comprehenſion of men or Angells. As therefore the <hi>Jews</hi> ſeeing Chriſt weeping over <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> his grave,<note place="margin">Joh. 11.</note> tooke notice of it as a ſpeciall evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this love that he bare him, and whiſpered one to another (as in that Text) <hi>See how he loved him.</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:112840:41"/> So when you ſee the Lord parting with his owne ſonne out of his own boſome, and freely giving him up to us to be borne and to dye for us, ſay as theſe <hi>Jews,</hi> and upon as infallible grounds and evidence, <hi>See how he loved us.</hi> And when you ſee the ſonne ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leave of his father, laying by all his robes of dignity and glory, which hee did enjoy at the right hand of his father to come downe to the earth to be borne for us, and to dye for us, to take our nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and in that nature to doe and to ſuffer ſuch grievous things as he did and ſuffered. When you ſee him reviled, buffeted, ſpit upon, ſcourged, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, crucified, when you ſee him upon the Croſſe, weeping, bleeding, dying for you, ſay as thoſe Jews did upon a leſſe occaſion,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>See how he loved us, ſurely his love to us was wonderfull, paſſing the love of women.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, hence I conclude, that henceforth the Lord will deny us nothing that is good for us, what will the Lord deny us that hath not denied us his ſonne to dye for us, he that ſpared not his ſonne, but gave him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him freely give us all things? Rom. 8.32. The argument concludes ſtrongly <hi>à majori,</hi> from the greater to the leſſe: when <hi>Acſah</hi> the daughter of <hi>Caleb,</hi> made ſuit to her father for a well of water,<note place="margin">Joſh. 15</note> thus ſhe accoaſts him, <hi>Thou haſt given me a South countrey, give me alſo a well of water,</hi> ſhe was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fident that he that had given her the greater would not deny her this ſmall re-requeſt, and ſhe was not deceaved in it for the Text tells us he granted her requeſt with advantage, <hi>Hee gave her the upper ſprings and the neather ſprings,</hi> ſo we
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:112840:41"/> may upon the ſame ground, perſwade our ſelves of our heavenly father, he hath given us the greater, he will not ſurely deny us the leſſer mercies, he hath given us <hi>Fields and Vineyards,</hi> hee will not deny us a <hi>well of water,</hi> but will give us <hi>the upper Springs and the neather Springs,</hi> hee will not deny us ſupply in our wants, comfort in our afflictions, protection in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, deliverance out of troubles, <hi>the neather Springs,</hi> nor will he deny us his ſpirit, his grace, remiſſion of our ſinnes, life everlaſting, and an inheritance in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>the upper Springs.</hi> Oh the happineſſe of the Saints and people of God in this his favour, hee hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too deare for them, thinks nothing too good for them, with what boldneſſe and <hi>confidence may they at all times draw neere the Throne of grace in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that they ſhall finde help in times of need?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I have done with the gift too, the gift of the ſonne, The child was borne the ſonn was given.</p>
               <p>BUt there is no gift,<note place="margin">The third ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall part.</note> nor giver but there is a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in this there are many, wee muſt not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look them, it is very fit wee ſhould reflect our eyes a little upon them too, to let them knowe their engagement by ſo great a gift that ſo thanks may be given <hi>by many for the gift beſtowed upon many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this pronoune tells us who they are to whom he was given, <hi>Nohis To us</hi> and twiſe for fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Nobis, To us.</hi> Becauſe indeed he is given to us in a twofold reſpect.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Firſt <hi>Nobis,</hi> To us <hi>excluſivè</hi> excluſively.</item>
                  <item>2 Secondly, <hi>Nobis</hi> To us <hi>incluſive</hi> incluſively.</item>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:112840:42"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nobis</hi> To us <hi>excluſivè</hi> excluding ſome. And</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nobis</hi> To us <hi>incluſivè</hi> including others.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Excluding firſt himſelfe, for hee was not borne for himſelfe, nor did he live to himſelfe, nor dye for himſelfe, but <hi>Nobis</hi> to Us, and <hi>Nobis</hi> for Us, <hi>for us men and for our ſalvation it was that he came down from heaven,</hi> as the <hi>Nicaene Creed</hi> in our <hi>Church Liturgie,</hi> puts us in minde. He needed not have done nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered any of theſe things for himſelfe, nor did hee thereby merit for himſelfe, nor could there any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be made to that glory and happineſſe which from all eternitie he did enjoy at the right hand of his father, unleſſe it were this, to ſee us happy with him, which before were miſerable: that hee might doe ſo he is content to become miſerable that wee might be happy, <hi>exinanire ſe, to emply himſelfe</hi> (ſaies one Text <hi>annihilare</hi> to annihilate (ſaies another) to emply himſelfe that he might fill us to make nothing of himſelfe that he might make ſomething of us, which were worſe then nothing, to become poore that we might be made rich, naked, that wee might be cloathed, harbourleſſe, that we might have man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in heaven a priſoner, that we might be ſet free: and at theſe great diſadvantages to exchange condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with us that we might be happy, and therefore truely <hi>Nobis</hi> to us was he given, and <hi>Nobis excluſivè,</hi> excluſively to us, not for himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, <hi>Nobis</hi> to us excluſively, in reſpect of the Angels,<note place="margin">Heb.</note> 
                  <hi>For he tooke not upon him the nature of Angells.</hi> And therefore when an Angell preacheth this doctrine, Luke 2.11. hee preacheth it not in the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:112840:42"/> firſt perſon, <hi>Nobis to us,</hi> but in the ſecond perſon,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus to you is borne this day in the Citty of David a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our which is Chriſt the Lord.</hi> He was not given for the Angells. whether it were becauſe their ſin was of a more higher nature, then the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> was, or whether it came within the compaſſe of the ſin ag<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy Ghoſt, or whether it was becauſe they ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with an higher hand againſt God, or that they ſinned againſt greater light, &amp; againſt greater grace, and greater ſtrength to ſubſiſt then <hi>Adam</hi> had, or whether it were becauſe their ſin was more volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary in that they ſinned without a tempter wee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute not. This we have reaſon even with admiration and aſtoniſhment, to take notice of his ſingular phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthropie, the freenes and the greatneſſe of his grace ſhewed to the loſt ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> in that when he ſaw them and the Apoſtate Angels both e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually loſt and undone, &amp; lying in a forlorne eſtate, and condition under his wrath and judgement of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, he was pleaſed (paſſing by the Angels and leaving them <hi>faſt bound in chaines of darkneſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to the iudgement of the great day</hi>) to caſt upon the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> a pittifull and a gracious eye,<note place="margin">Judae.</note> and to finde out a meanes to recover and to reſtore them againe by this his ſonne. Say no more, <hi>What is man that thou art thus mindfull of him, or the ſon of man that thou thus viſiteſt him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt made him lower then the Angells,</hi> for in this reſpect the Lord hath made him higher then the Angels. <hi>For he took not upon him the nature of Angels, but he took upon him the ſeed of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> And therefore ſecondly is he ſaid to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:112840:43"/> 
                  <hi>Nobis</hi> to us, To us excluſively, excluding the Angels falne, which ſtood in as great need of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption as man did.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Againe, <hi>Nobis</hi> to us <hi>incluſivè,</hi> including all thoſe that receive benefit by Chriſt, and ſo this <hi>Nobis</hi> to us, may be underſtood firſt <hi>Perſonally</hi> of <hi>Iſay,</hi> and all ſuch faithfull ſervants of Gods as <hi>Iſay</hi> was. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Nationallly</hi> To us, that is to us <hi>Jews</hi> the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> the people of the Covenant, to whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the promiſes, and in particular this of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> deſcending of us. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Vniverſally</hi> to us, that is to all nations of the world, <hi>parum eſt,</hi> ſaith the Lord <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. <hi>It is a light thing that thou ſhouldſt be my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to raiſe up the Tribes of Iacob, &amp; to reſtore the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of Iſrael. I will alſo give thee for a light to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles that thou maiſt be my ſalvation unto the ends of the earth.</hi> So that the Jew cannot ſay to the Gentile he was given for us, and not for you, nor the Gentile to the Jew, he was given for us and not for you, nor the Greeke to the Barbarian he was given for us &amp; not for you, nor the Barbarian to the Greek hee was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to us and not to you. Nor theſe that were under the Law to thoſe that were before the Law hee was given to us and not to you, nor theſe that live under the Goſpell to thoſe that lived under the Law hee is given to us and not to you, for he is given to them all, to the Gentile as well as to the Jew, the Greek as well as to the Barbarian, to thoſe that were under the Law, aſwell as to thoſe that are under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to thoſe that were before, both aſwell as to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them both, and therefore let all theſe take
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:112840:43"/> comfort in him, let them all challenge their intereſt in him, and every of them with hope &amp; confidence ſay, as in the Text, <hi>Unto us</hi> this ſon is given.</p>
               <p>I am not willing here (though it falls juſt in my way) to engage in that great queſtion which hath ſo much troubled the world touching the Latitude and extent of this gift we are ſpeaking of, to whom, or to how many it may appertaine or was intended, I know there are errours on both hands while ſome extend it not onely to all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen. &amp;c.</hi> I had once a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute with a Knight in Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne ſhiere, one <hi>S. W. Hickman,</hi> a zealous <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniſt</hi> in this point.</note> but even to the Divells too and apoſtate Angells, unto all which they ſay he was given, and by whom in the end they ſhall all bee reſtored &amp; ſaved. Others on the other hand limit it to a certaine definite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men, fore thought on long before the world was for that purpoſe, and then by an unchangeable, immoveable and irreſiſtable decree ſet forth and deſignd to ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt in time to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them and they to him by the father, and this number ſo inconſiderable in compariſon of the reſt that periſh, that by their computation, and account ſcarſly the ten thouſandth man of the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> ſhall be ſaved. But who are we that we ſhould thus limit the holy one of Iſrael, and why ſhould our eye be evill if his be good. Indeed this doctrine if true to thoſe few they ſpeak of (how few ſo ever they be) muſt needs be pretious, it magnifies beyond meaſure, the riches of that gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to them wards which hath made ſuch a difference where it found none, it binds them for ever to love much to whom ſo much is given and forgiven, but what a ſad
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:112840:44"/> yea what a deſperate condition doth it caſt the whole world of the reſt of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> into? Nay what an imputation doth it lay upon the Lord God in the higheſt of his attributes, the attribute of his grace and goodneſſe unto his creature, as if hee did make the world wel nigh for no other intent, but that thereby he might have an occaſion to win ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour unto himſelfe in one of his attributes, the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute of his juſtice in deſtroying it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But ſurely when I conſider the nature of our heavenly Father, as he hath beene pleaſed to make himſelfe out unto his creature both in his word and workes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> when I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the value, the ineſtimable value of the price that was laid down for our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> even the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood of the ſonne of God, a price ſufficient to have ranſom'd a thouſand worlds, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that by giving his ſonne to dye for us, the Lord had found out a way whereby he had made the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all men poſſible without prejudice, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of his truth or juſtice, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> when I read the glorious propheſies of the Prophets of old, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of the Evangelicall Prophet of the abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of grace purchaſed unto the Church by the Meſſiah &amp; the glory of his kingdome, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> when I read of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel between the 2 Adams, &amp; how in every reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it the ſecond hath the preeminence. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> When I conſider the vaſtnes of the Emperean heavens, the habitation of the Saints, the place appointed for the juſt to dwell in,<note place="margin">Revel.</note> A ſpace that no man can meaſure for multitudes, that no man can number. I am eaſily perſuaded to beleeve that the Lord by Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112840:44"/> hath opened a greater and a wider dore into the kingdome of heaven then theſe men are perſwaded of: &amp; that it doth neither ſtand with the nature of his grace and goodneſſe, and love to his creature nor with the honour of Chriſt his Mediatorſhip, nor ſuit with the price of that blood that was paid for our ranſome, nor with the glory of the propheſies of old or the promiſes ſince of the abundance of grace, and glory of Chriſts kingdome, nor the latitude of the covenant made unto the Church, that the remnant of <hi>Adams</hi> ſons that returne ſhould be ſo ſmall or the berries upon the Olive tree ſo few and ſo thinne as ſome imagine.</p>
               <p>But to hold our ſelves cloſe to the word in this matter as tis fit we ſhould. Underſtand here <hi>Nobis, To us,</hi> in that ſence in which our Lord himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it, ſpeaking of this very gift, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten ſonne to the end that whoſoever beleeved in him ſhould not periſh, but have life everlaſting. Nobis to us,</hi> in that ſenſe in which <hi>S. Paul</hi> underſtands it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>As by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of one, judgement came upon all men to condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo by the righteouſneſſe. of one, the free gift came upon all men to iuſtification of life. Nobis</hi> to us, in that ſenſe in which the ſame Apoſtle underſtands it, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. when he ſaies, <hi>God would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> And verſ. 7. of the ſame Chapter, <hi>which gave himſelfe a ranſome for all,</hi> For <hi>ſinners.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. for the <hi>ungodly. Rom.</hi> 5.6. For <hi>his enimies,</hi> verſ. 10. For <hi>them that deny him:</hi> 2. Pet. 2.1. Even for <hi>them that are damn'd,</hi> in the ſame
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:112840:45"/> Text the latter end of the verſe. Let no man here charge me with Arminianiſme in that I preach up grace ſo high, or if he doe, I paſſe not much, as long as by his own confeſſion tis grace that I preach, let me preach it as high as I can, I ſhal therein be found more faithfull to my Maſter then they that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate, conceale, ſuppreſſe, or monopolize it. Upon theſe teſtimonies of holy writ, I am perſwaded to beleeve that there is no ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> that ever was or ſhall be borne in the world, but the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> when he tooke his nature upon him did ſomething for him, ſo much at leaſt as hath freed him of the guilt of the ſin of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> imputed to him, &amp; hath put him upon a new ſcore and a new account with the Lord God, &amp; made over ſalvation to him upon a new covenant purchaſed by his blood made upon better tearmes, conditions, and promiſes then the old was, &amp; that he ſhall never periſh everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unleſſe he forfeit his ſalvation a ſecond time.</p>
               <p>All the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, <hi>de modo applicandi,</hi> about the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how Chriſt and the grace by him comes to bee applied to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeing there are ſo many nations that never heard ſo much as of his name, or knowe what the Goſpell meanes, of which I ſhall by Gods helpe ſhortly give you an account, and I hope ſome reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſatisfaction, in a Treatiſe which I have now under my hand upon the parallell between the two <hi>Adams</hi> compar'd in the fift Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Romans; In the meane time reſt upon this, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That <hi>with God all things are poſsible.</hi> And (as in the caſe of infants) ſo of theſe, where their ignorance is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:112840:45"/> and the meanes whereby that ſhould bee cured, to them impoſſible to be attained, although they cannot apply themſelves unto Chriſt, the Lord of his abundant grace and goodneſſe can apply Chriſt unto them? <hi>Who is found of them that ſought him not, and ſeeks out them that asked not after him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Know farther, that there are different degrees of ſalvation, hath the Lord but one bleſſing for all his ſonnes? or but one heaven to put his redeemed ones in, or but one ſort of manſions in that heaven? what think you is the meaning of that Scripture. 1. Tim. 4 10. <hi>Who is the Saviour of all men, eſpecially of them that beleeve.</hi> Although it is certaine they are in no wiſe capable of that ſpeciall ſalvation peculiar to beleivers, yet I truſt it is no hereſie, neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt grace, nor charity to hope that (walking up with all their might to that light which they have) by the mercy of God, and the merits of the Mediator, they may be found capable of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of ſalvation, and of an eſtate (at leaſt) above that of perdition in the lake of everlaſting burnings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider thirdly, that at the laſt and great day of account, though all the world ſhall bee judged at one barre, yet they ſhall not all be juded by one Law but the meere Gentile by the Law of nature, the meere <hi>Jew</hi> by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; the Chriſtian by the Goſpell, the Law of grace, &amp; according to their conformity to theſe three Laws ſhall they receive their doome, their <hi>Euge</hi> or their <hi>Apage,</hi> Rom. 2.12. But to leave them <hi>to ſtand or fall to their own maſter:</hi> give me leave to turne my ſelfe to you (Bel) and to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112840:46"/> ſpeak ſomething to you by way of application, and ſo I will conclude this point: And I have three things to ſay to you concerning this matter.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is to put you in mind of your great happineſſe, and priviledge that you have above theſe poore people we ſpeake of in this particular, inaſmuch as the Lord hath dealt more liberally with you then with them he hath done, that which concerning them is but a queſtion, is to you out of queſtion, to you <hi>is this ſalvation ſent,</hi> which to them is denied, <hi>to you this ſonne is given,</hi> to you is hee come to you, he offers himſelfe in his Goſpell, in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, how happy are you if you can ſee your happineſſe to whom ſuch meanes of happineſſe are afforded, what a price have you in your hands, to get knowledge, life, and ſalvation, what faire oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to build up your ſelves in grace here, and to lay for your ſelves a foundation of glory hereafter, bleſſed are your eyes that ſee the things that you ſee and your eares that heare the things that you heare, which Kings and Prophets have deſired to ſee and heare and have not, and which to the greateſt part of the world beſides hath been denied?</p>
               <p>But how miſerable are you, if in the midſt of all theſe meanes you ſhould miſcarry, <hi>if ſuch a light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come into the world you ſhould love darkneſſe rather then light,</hi> if having ſuch <hi>a price put into your hands to get knowledge, grace, and glory,</hi> you like <hi>fooles ſhould have no heart?</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If (the Lord having freely given you his ſon) you ſhould not receave him, how ill muſt the Lord needs take this at your hands, &amp; how heavily
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112840:46"/> will he charge you another day as being in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that <hi>wilfully forſake their own mercy that refuſe and diſpiſe great ſalvation, and thruſt from them the kingdome of heaven, he would have gathered you but you would not be gathered, he would have healed you, but you would not be healed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Wherefore the next duty charged upon you is this: if the Lord hath ſo freely given you his ſon then is it your duty with all joy and thankfulneſſe to receive him, tis not the ſending of his ſonne that will make you happy, nor the giving, but the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of this gift that will enrich you, receive him therefore by your ready and cheerefull entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpell in which he offers himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, receive him into your hearts by Faith, into your houſes by Charity, into your affections by Joy and Praiſe and into your practiſe too, by imitation, though he be given to us of the Father, yet he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver actually ours till he be thus ours, by a partciular reception &amp; application of him to our ſelves &amp; our own ſoules, Tis not the <hi>Univerſall Nobis</hi> that makes him ours, that ſpeaks him at too great a diſtance, nor the <hi>Nationall Nobis</hi> that gives us an intereſt in him, thats yet too generall, tis the <hi>Perſonall nobis</hi> that brings him home to us, and gives us aſſurance, nay nor that neither untill we come yet neerer home by changing the number, the plurall into the ſingular, when inſteed of <hi>Nobis natus,</hi> and <hi>Nobis datus,</hi> we can with old <hi>Simeon</hi> take up this child and hugge him in our armes by a more ſpeciall application and ſay <hi>mihi natus</hi> and <hi>mihi datus, unto mee</hi> this child is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112840:47"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:112840:47"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:112840:48"/> borne, and <hi>unto me</hi> this Son is given.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third duty charged upon us in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this gift ſhall conclude this diſcourſe. And that followes <hi>ex congruo</hi> by way of congruity. It is thankfulneſſe. It is very fit that <hi>thanks ſhould bee given by many, for the gift beſtowed upon many.</hi> Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we have been of the taking hand, all hath been, <hi>to us, to us</hi> the childe, and <hi>to us</hi> the Sonn, <hi>to us</hi> the birth, and <hi>to us</hi> the gift all hath beene <hi>to us,</hi> but what? will there be nothing lookt for from us think you for all this good communicated to us, No returne to bee made upon the receipt of ſo great a gift? Nothing to the Father that gave him, Nothing to the Sonne that was given, Nothing to the child that was born for us, and to us? Yes ſurely, ſomething to them all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, thanks to the Father that gave the Son, <hi>We thanke thee O Father Lord of Heaven and Earth,</hi> that thou wert pleaſed to ſpare and part with thine owne Son out of thine own boſome for our ſakes, that by his merit and mediation (of ſons of wrath) we might be made ſonnes of grace, ſons of adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and coheyers with this thy ſon of an inheritance in glory. Now thanks be to God for this unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gift.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, thanks to the Sonne that was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be given, and content to ſubmit to ſuch hard conditions to reſcue us out of that miſerable thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into which we had caſt our ſelves, and under which without him helpes, and hopeleſſe wee had lyen for ever.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And thirdly, thanks to the child for his love
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:112840:48"/> ſhewed to the Children of men, in that for their ſakes he was content to become a child, to bee con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceived in the wombe, borne of a woman, and in his perſon to beare all the infirmities of infancy &amp; child<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hood, that ſo he might merit for them the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their natures, and by the holineſſe of his, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to them purifie theirs and cure them of their Originall ſin even in the wombe.</p>
               <p>But what? Nothing but thankes for all this? Yes ſomething more, though it be not much that we can doe in compenſation of ſo great love and kindneſſe, nor much that we can give by way of returne, yet let us give what we can, let us doe what we can. <hi>Let us give up our ſelves, ſoules and bodies a living ſacrifice unto him,</hi> which gave up his to be a dying ſacrifice for us. Let us love the Child, reverence the Sonne, honour the Father, ever more admiring &amp; adoring, the <hi>Philanthropie</hi> of the child, the humility of the Sonne, the wiſdome, power, grace, juſtice, truth, and mercy of the Father, all ſet aworke in this great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne undertaken meerely for the good of mankind, <hi>for us men and for our ſalvation,</hi> For <hi>unto us the Child was borne,</hi> And <hi>unto us the Sonne was given,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from us, and from all the hoaſts of Heaven, from men and from Angels, let there bee aſcribed unto them all (as is moſt due) All glory, honour, power, praiſe, might, Majeſtie, thankſgiving, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and dominion with <hi>Halleluiah</hi> For evermore <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
